<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first booke of questions and answers vpon Genesis Containing those questions that are most eminent and pertinent, vpon the sixe first chapters of the same booke: collected out of ancient and recent writers; both briefly and subtilly propounded and expounded, by Alexander Rosse, of Aberdine, preacher at Saint Maries neere Southampton, and one of his Maiesites chaplaines.</title>
            <author>Ross, Alexander, 1591-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11059</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21325</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112086</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847345</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847345</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12378</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11059)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12378)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1582:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first booke of questions and answers vpon Genesis Containing those questions that are most eminent and pertinent, vpon the sixe first chapters of the same booke: collected out of ancient and recent writers; both briefly and subtilly propounded and expounded, by Alexander Rosse, of Aberdine, preacher at Saint Maries neere Southampton, and one of his Maiesites chaplaines.</title>
                  <author>Ross, Alexander, 1591-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 116 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes, for Francis Constable, dwelling in Pauls Church-yard, ouer-against the great North doore, at the signe of the white Lyon,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes frontispiece, opposite A1, title page.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis --  Examinations, questions, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:12378:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of harpist</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12378:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FIRST BOOKE OF QVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIONS AND ANSWERS vpon Geneſis.</p>
            <p>Containing thoſe queſtions that are <hi>moſt eminent and pertinent, vpon the ſixe</hi> firſt Chapters of the ſame Booke: Collected out of ancient and <hi>recent Writers;</hi> Both briefly and ſubtilly propounded and expounded, By <hi>Alexander Roſſe,</hi> of <hi>Aberdine,</hi> Preacher at Saint <hi>Maries</hi> neere <hi>Southampton,</hi> and one of <hi>his Maieſties Chaplaines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by NICHOLAS OKES, for <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Conſtable,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Pauls Church-yard,</hi> ouer-againſt the great North <hi>doore, at the ſigne of the white Lyon.</hi> 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12378:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12378:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>TO THE RIGHT Honorable, <hi>Francis,</hi> Lord <hi>Verulam, Lord high</hi> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. In this Vniuerſe (Right Honorable)</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are onely two things that are the obiects both of Contemplation and of Admiration, that is, the Creator, and the creature: amongſt the creatures onely two, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and men; in man onely two parts; the bodie and ſoule; in the ſoule, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly two faculties, the mind and the will; in the minde, two things onely; <hi>God and his Word:</hi> the Word of God is two-fold;
<pb facs="tcp:12378:3"/>
internall and externall: the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall word is two-fold; ſpoken and writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: the written word hath two parts; the old, and new Teſtament; the old containeth two, <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; and <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaketh of theſe two we formerly mentioned, which onely are the obiects of our contemplations; euen the Creator, and the creature: the Creator wee know <hi>via negationis, emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentiae, &amp; cauſalitatis;</hi> but we know the creatures, if they be ſenſible, <hi>Cognitione ſenſitiua;</hi> if not, <hi>intellectiua:</hi> but proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this life wee know not God, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his Eſſence, (for how ſhall wee know him, of whom there can not be framed either <hi>Species intelligibiles</hi> or <hi>ſenſibiles,</hi> ſeeing that knowledge is <hi>per ſpecies?</hi>) yet in part we know him, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard wee haue ſome knowledge of his perſonall and eſſentiall properties, of his effects and operations.</p>
            <p>Which knowledge is but ſmall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our finite ſcience cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend
<pb facs="tcp:12378:3"/>
that infinite Eſſence. For if a ſhell cannot contain the Sea, which is a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; much leſſe can our ſoules him, that is our Creator. The cauſe then why the Owle can not behold the Sunne, is in the eies of the Owle, not in the Sunne: ſo, that we cannot know God perfectly, is not in God, who is moſt perfect, but in vs that are imperfect; <hi>&amp; quidquid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitur, recipitur ad modum recipientis, non ad modum recepti.</hi> Then our knowledge is ſo weake, that wee neither know the firſt effector, whoſe Eſſence is moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent; neither his firſt effect (I meane the firſt matter) whoſe exiſtence is moſt impotent.</p>
            <p>Yet a more eminent knowledge of our Maker haue wee than the <hi>Pagans,</hi> who only know him by his works, but we by his words: they by contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; we by inſpiration: they by ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>Images,</hi> we by his eſſentiall <hi>Image:</hi> they by painted and carued ſtones; we by that ſtone which the builders did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe,
<pb facs="tcp:12378:4"/>
which became the head of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, which was cut out of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine without hands, which brake all their <hi>Images</hi> to powder, vpon which are ſeuen eies, euen that tried and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtone, that was laid in <hi>Sion:</hi> by him (I ſay) in whom the God-head dwels bodily, in whom are hid al the treaſures of wiſedome and knowledge, haue we the knowledge of our Creator; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom, our ſcience is but igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and our meditations, vexations.</p>
            <p>This is that internal word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by whom, and by whoſe ſpirit was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and written this externall word contained in the Scripture, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the which word, the Creator and the creature is only to be knowne, not only in all, but in euery part thereof, no leſſe than the ſoule is all, in all the body, and all in euery part of the ſame: ſo is know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in this word. Now this externall word differeth from Chriſt the internal word of the Father, as in vs the word,
<pb facs="tcp:12378:4"/>
which is in our mind, doth differ from that, which is in our mouth and books: our internall ſpeech and reaſon, is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated in the ſoule, and of the ſoule, and is coetaneall with the ſoule: ſo is <hi>Chriſt</hi> begotten in the Father, and of the Father, and is coeternall with the Father; but the word that is in our mouth and books, is accidental, and the effect of our internall word; ſo is that word, which is in the Scripture, and in the mouth of Chriſts ſeruants acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, and the effect of Chriſt the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall word of the Father; who is both <hi>ratio &amp; oratio Patris,</hi> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is both. Our ſoules, <hi>cognitione directa,</hi> doe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand many things that are without the ſoule, but <hi>cognitione reflexa,</hi> ſhe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth her ſelfe, and then, <hi>idem eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligens &amp; id quod intelligitur;</hi> ſo God doth know all his creatures, which are but his effects: but in vnderſtanding himſelfe from all eternitie, he doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get that knowledge of himſelfe, and in
<pb facs="tcp:12378:5"/>
himſelfe, which is himſelfe, euen <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his owne wiſedome and knowledge.</p>
            <p>Yet there is great relation betweene Chriſt, Gods internall Word, and the Scripture, his externall word, for as none knoweth the Father but by the Sonne, his word internall; ſo none knoweth the Father &amp; the Son, but by the Scripture, his Word externall. As the internall word was, <hi>Principium eſſendi,</hi> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the creatures; ſo the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall is <hi>Principium cognoſcendi,</hi> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of knowledge. As nothing did exiſt before the word internall, ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was ſpoken before the word ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall. As by the internall Word the world was created: ſo by the externall word the world is inſtructed. As that word was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued of the holy Ghoſt: ſo this word was inſpired by the holy Ghoſt. As that word was perſecuted by the Iewes, and crucified by the Roman <hi>Pilate:</hi> ſo this word hath beene falſified by the Iewes, and wounded by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb facs="tcp:12378:5"/>
               <hi>Prelate.</hi> As it was held vnlawful for the people to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſe with that Word: ſo it was held vnlawfull, for the Lay people to conuerſe with this word. As the Iewes did more regard their tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions than that word; ſo the Romans doe more regard their vnwritten lies, than this Word. As that Word was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in a garden, and kept ſure from his Diſciples: ſo was this word buried in an vnknowne tongue, and kept cloſe from Chriſtians: &amp; as this word, in deſpite of the Iewes, was reſtored to life; ſo this word, in diſpite of the Popes, is brought forth againe to light.</p>
            <p>This is that word, the Author, obiect, ſubiect, end, and ground whereof, is God, for verity admirable; for antiquity venerable; for ſanctity incomparable; for vtility ineſtimable: here is light for the blind, life for the dead, food for the hungry, drinke for the thirſty: here is the tree of life, the fountaines of liuing wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Manna the food of Angels, pearles
<pb facs="tcp:12378:6"/>
and other rich Iewels; here is a banquet of many diſhes; an Apothecaries ſhop with many medicines; a ſweet garden of many flowres; an Armour-houſe with many weapons; here is ſalt to ſeaſon, milke to ſtrengthen, wine to comfort, and hony to ſweeten; here the cold may be warmed, the weary refreſhed, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked clothed, and the filthy clenſed. If thou deſireſt light and perfection, here is Vrim and Thummim; if the ſight of thy fins, here is the golden candleſticke; if thou wilt waſh thy hands and feete, here is the brazen lauer; wilt thou bee purged from thy leproſie? here is the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Iordan;</hi> wilt thou flooriſh like a Bay tree? thou muſt be planted by this riuer; wilt thou bring forth much fruite? thou muſt be ſowne with this ſeed; wilt thou ſacrifice thy ſins to <hi>God?</hi> thou muſt kill them with this ſword; wilt thou go to the kingdome of heauen? this is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way; here is the firy pillar and the
<pb facs="tcp:12378:6"/>
cloud to conduct thee to <hi>Canaan;</hi> and here is the Star that will leade thee to find out the Son of righteouſn, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> that bright morning Starre, with whom we ſhall ſhine in eternity of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as Stars in the firmament.</p>
            <p>In this word then muſt we conuerſe both day and night, not in curious ſearching, and prodigious ſpeculation; but in ſerious weeping, and religious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration; neither muſt our minds be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with terreſtriall and infernal oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupations: but they muſt be filled with celeſtiall and ſupernall meditations. Therfore if we will profit here, we muſt caſt off all carnall affection, that wee may receiue for our weary ſoules eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall refection: for if no beaſt could touch the mountaine, and heare Gods Law: why ſhould beaſtly minds touch the Bible, and read Gods Law? And in ſearching this Word, let vs not in it ſearch for riches and honour to our
<pb facs="tcp:12378:7"/>
ſelues, which is to ſeek for dirt amongſt Iewels, and poyſon amongſt medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to ouerthrow ourſelues: but let vs ſearch for him, who only is ſufficient to content our ſoules within our bodies, as hee was the only efficient to preſent our ſoules into our bodies. Therfore we conclude with <hi>Auguſtine, Scriptura &amp; creatura ad hoc ſunt, vt ipſe quaeratur, ipſe diligatur, &amp; qui ipſam creauit, &amp; qui illam inſpirauit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The internall and eternall generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the word, was not knowne to the Gentiles: but was obſcured with an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure fable of <hi>Minerua,</hi> begotten of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piters</hi> braine, by the which alſo they did ſignifie learned notions conceaued in the mind, &amp; expreſſed by word or writ.</p>
            <p>Then, to be ſhort (right Honourable) heere I doe offer to your tuition and fruition my <hi>Minerua,</hi> not begotten of my braine, but in my braine; neither is ſhe armed with a helmet, <hi>aegis,</hi> and a
<pb facs="tcp:12378:7"/>
ſpeare to terrifie <hi>Momus;</hi> and therefore the more deſirous ſhee is to ſhelter her ſelf vnder the ſhaddow of your Honors patronage, being perſwaded that you are both a Patrone &amp; a patterne of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the fruits whereof haue not only refreſhed the hearts and eares of great Brittaine: but with <hi>Dedalean</hi> wings they haue bin tranſported beyond the <hi>Ocean;</hi> ſo that <hi>Rhodanus, Betis,</hi> and <hi>Rhenus,</hi> haue ſeaſoned their ſiluer ſtreames with the delicious taſte of your learned fruits. Then what remaines,
<q>
                  <l>quam vt ocior Icaro</l>
                  <l>Viſas gementis littora Boſphori,</l>
                  <l>Sirteſque Getulas canorus,</l>
                  <l>Ales Hypereboroſque campos?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, your Honor being a Father and Patrone of iuſtice, if any wrong be offered to her by <hi>Momus,</hi> ſhe may bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fly to the Chancery for ſuccor: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I hope, that as your Honor hath permitted your glorious titles to grace her Frontiſpice; ſo you wil not refuſe to
<pb facs="tcp:12378:8"/>
beautifie her with your gracious aſpect and reſpect. That God, which hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted you to ſo great dignities in this world, preſerue your body and ſoule, and crowne you in the World to come with bleſſed Immortality.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors in all duty, euer to command, ALEXANDER ROSSE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:12378:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Ad illuſtriſsimum Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> ſupremum Angliae Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellarium, Alexandri Roſſaei <hi>Epigramma.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>PAcis amans, virtutis honos, decor inclyte gentis,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Muſarum</hi> docti gloria magna chori.</l>
            <l>Auro <hi>Iuno</hi> beat te, lauro <hi>Phoebus Apollo,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Linguâ <hi>Mercurius,</hi> frontis honore <hi>Venus.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Frontis honor moritur, floreſcit gloria linguae,</l>
            <l>Aurea ſceptra cadunt, laurea ſerta manent.</l>
            <l>Tu laurum praefers auro, <hi>Venerique Süadam,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Plus tibi luce <hi>Themis,</hi> plus tibi laude <hi>Charis.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Propterea aeternum tua fama vigebit in aevum,</l>
            <l>Quod peritura fugis, quod vigetura petis.</l>
            <l>En tenues noſtrae mittunt tibi dona <hi>Camoenae,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Non ſatis ampla tibi, ſint licet apta mihi.</l>
            <l>Non <hi>Arabum</hi> meſſes, non <hi>Indica</hi> munera mittunt,</l>
            <l>Aut <hi>Nili</hi> varias luxuriantis opes.</l>
            <l>Non pictas croco aut radiantes murice vestes,</l>
            <l>Aut aurum rutilis quod vehit <hi>Hermus</hi> aquis.</l>
            <l>Sed tibi chartaceum mittunt cum carmine donum.</l>
            <l>Et ſterilis noſter qualia fundit ager.</l>
            <l>Accipe propterea placido pia munera vultu,</l>
            <l>Sinceri officij pignora certa mei.</l>
            <l>Noſtram ſi facilis reſpexeris inclyte <hi>Muſam,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Te redeunte die, te pereunte canam.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:12378:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12378:9"/>
            <head>The Argument.</head>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVHo wrote theſe bookes of</hi> Moſes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Himſelfe: proofe; hee was the firſt that writ in the world. Secondly, The holy Ghoſt teſtifieth the ſame, <hi>Exo. 24.4. Deu. 31.9.</hi> and Chriſt, <hi>Iohn 1.45.</hi> and <hi>5.46.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When wrote he this firſt Booke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Before the Iſraelites went from <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt:</hi> Reaſ. <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe then, feeding his Father-in-lawes ſheepe <hi>40.</hi> yeeres, in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,</hi> he was moſt at leyſure to write. Rea. <hi>2.</hi> To comfort the Hebrewes, beeing oppreſſed with Egyptian ſeruitude; for in this Booke they read the life and death of their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours; their courage; patience; vertue in affliction; Gods promiſes to <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12378:10"/>
that after.<hi>400</hi> yeares ſeruitude in <hi>Egypt,</hi> they ſhould be deliuered, and inioy the land of <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How came</hi> Moſes <hi>to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theſe things contained in this Booke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Either by reuelation from God, or by tradition of his Anceſtors: for the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theſe things <hi>Moſes</hi> had from <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> children; they of <hi>Ioſeph;</hi> he of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob; Iacob</hi> of <hi>Iſaac;</hi> he of <hi>Abraham;</hi> and he of <hi>Shem; Shem</hi> of <hi>Noe;</hi> he of <hi>Methuſalem;</hi> and he of <hi>Adam,</hi> with whom he liued <hi>243.</hi> yeeres.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12378:10"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:12378:11"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12378:11"/>
            <head>Queſtions on the firſt <hi>Chapter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>As the world created, or eternall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Created. 1. There can bee but one eternall. 2. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the eternity of the world. 3. They that hold it eternall, can bring no ſound reaſon. 4. The moſt ancient monuments or records amongſt the heathen, are not ſo old as the flood of <hi>Noah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Could God make more worlds then one?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: for he is almighty, and hee made it not of any mater: for that ſhould haue bin ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted: but more he would not, becauſe hee being one, delights in vnity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:12378:12"/>Q. <hi>Why in Hebrew ſaith</hi> Moſes, <hi>Gods created? ioyning the noune plurall, with the verbe ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſignifie the myſtery of the Trinitie, one eſſence in three perſons. 2. It is the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Hebrew phraſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why in the beginning of this booke, ſpeaketh</hi> Moſes <hi>only of heauen and earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe by the name of heauen, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends all celeſtiall bodies, and by the name of earth the 4. elements: for water is in the earth, &amp; fire and aire, as witneſſe the ſprings, exhalations, or earthquakes, and burning mountaines, or hote waters.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Did God create the earth moueable or not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Immoueable, <hi>Iob</hi> 38. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 93. and 104. this is vnderſtood, in reſpect of the whole earth: yet it is moued in reſpect of parts, by earthquakes. <hi>Iob</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Of what figure is the earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Round, <hi>Eſay</hi> the 40. This figure is moſt perfect, capable, ancient.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is the earth vnder the water or not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Vnder, becauſe heauieſt: yet <hi>Exo.</hi> 20. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 24. and 136. it ſeemes the water is vnder the earth; but it is to be vnderſtood, that a great part of the earth was made higher then the waters, for mans habitation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12378:12"/>Q. <hi>Why cannot the whole earth moue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe hee is in his natural place, which if it ſhould moue, it ſhould aſcend: and this is againſt the nature of the earth.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is vnderſtood by the ſpirit that moued vpon the waters?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A wind, which often in Scripture is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a ſpirit, or the holy Ghoſt, or the power and mighty operation of God: which alſo is often called by the name of Spirit: in this ſence the Spirit of God is ſayd to carry <hi>Elias</hi> to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; and to haue caught away <hi>Philip, Acts</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is God brought in, ſpeaking in the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſhew his abſolute power, whoſe word is his worke. 2. The ſecond perſon in Trinity, the word eſſential of the Father, by whom the world was created.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was the light firſt created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To beautifie al the reſt of the creatures. 2. The world was created in 6. daies, which could not bee diſtinguiſhed without the light and darkenes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was this light ſpirituall, ſuch as God is ſayd to inhabit, as Chriſt is called the light of the world, and the Apoſtles light, the regenerate light?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: but corporall and ſenſible, firſt, the darkenes that went before, was ſenſible: <hi>ergo,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:12378:13"/>
light. 2. By this light the 3. dayes were diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed before the creation of the ſun: but they were ſenſible. 3. This Narration of <hi>Moſes</hi> is hiſtoricall, not allegoricall.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Then what light was this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not the light of the elemental fire, nor of a light cloud, nor of water, but of the ſun: which was the firſt day diffuſed through the whole hemiſphere: the 4. was collected into the globe of the ſun we ſee. The 1. day this light had but one common property to illuminate: the 4. it had particular vertues to bring out particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar effects. 3. This light, the 4. day began to bee cauſe of generation and corruption, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of time, the cauſe of increaſe, and decreaſe in the moone.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How did this light before the</hi> 4. <hi>day, distinguiſh the day from night?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In moouing from eaſt to weſt; and from weſt to eaſt, by the motion of the 1. ſpheare.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In what place of heauen was this light crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In the eaſt, for this light returning to this ſame point of the eaſt, from which it went, made a naturall day.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhen was heauen and earth created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Before the firſt day, in reſpect of their ſubſtance and matter, but in the ſixe dayes, in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12378:13"/>
reſpect of their forme and perfection.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is meant by the firmament that ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth the waters from the waters?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The aire, and ſtarry heauens, with all the ſpheres betweene, which do ſeparate the watry clouds, from theſe waters below: but properly the lower regio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the aire doth ſeparate theſe waters, which are generated in the ſingle regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from the waters below, which low region is called by the name of the whole firmament.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are theſe waters aboue the firmament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not Angels, as <hi>Origen,</hi> not waters pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called, aboue the ſtars, as <hi>Baſil</hi> would haue: for their natural place is below, and there is no vſe of them aboue the ſtarres: neither the heauen called the <hi>Criſtalline,</hi> which hath neither the ſubſtance, ſimilitude or qualities of water: but by theſe waters wee vnderſtand the watery clouds, aboue this lower region in the aire. Theſe waters in other places are ſayd to be aboue the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that is, aboue the aire, which in Scripture is called heauen.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How made God the drie land to appeare?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By cauſing the earth, which before was plaine, to ſwell with mountaines. 2. By the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which before were ſpred ouer the whole earth, to betake themſelues to one place.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Then were there mountaines before the flood?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:12378:14"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: for the flood roſe 15. cubits higher then the mountaines: the mountaines are called eternall, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 76. Wiſedome is ancienter then the mountaines, <hi>Pro.</hi> 8. They make the earth the comelier, more fruiteful, more commodious for man and beaſt: they hold out the ſeas from ouer-flowing the earth: out of them ſprings and riuers proceed: they defend the valleies from the raging of the windes, that without them, the earth could not be before the flood.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is the earth or ſeas higheſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The earth: for all riuers run into the ſeas naturally, becauſe they flow downewards. 2. Men are ſaid to go down into the ſeas in ſhips, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. Again, if the ſeas were higher, ſhips ſhould ſayle ſwifter to the land then from it. 4. The farther we were in the ſea, we ſhould ſee the land the better.</p>
            <p>Ob. <hi>But</hi> Pſa. 104. <hi>and</hi> 33. <hi>it ſeemes that the waters are higher then the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaks of the ſprings that are generated in the mountaines, or of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery clouds that couer the hills: in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 33. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſpeakes of the miraculous ſtanding of the red ſea.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Were briers, thornes, and poyſonable hearbes created before mans fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: becauſe theſe are parts of this world,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12378:14"/>
without which it is not perfect: and although poyſonable hearbs are not fit for meate, they are good for phyſicke.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In what time of the yeere was the world created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In the Autumne, becauſe the Iewes before they departed from <hi>Egypt,</hi> began their yeere in Autumne, and alſo before the ſtood: for the flood began in the ſecond month, that is, about the month of Nouember. 2. The Iewes <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. are commanded to keepe the feaſts of Tabernacles in the end of the yeere, that is, in Autumne, when fruits are ripe: and alſo this ſame feaſt in the beginning of the yeere, <hi>Chap.</hi> 34. nature alſo ſhews, that Autumne is the end of the yeere, by the maturity of the fruite, and falling of the leaues from the trees. It is alſo the beginning of the yeere, as the yong ſeeds bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of the earth do teſtifie. Laſtly, in the creation the fruits of the trees were ripe, and ready to be eaten.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Were the ſtarres created the fourth day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, in reſpect of their light, motions and operations: but they were made the 1. day in reſpect of their ſubſtance, for they are the thicker part of the ſpheres.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why were the ſtars created after the planets?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe God will ſhew his power, which in producing of plants, doth not depend on the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12378:15"/>
ſtarres. 2. To keepe the people from idolatrie, whom he knew would be bent to worſhip the ſtarres, when they conſider their beauty, moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and operation, in producing hearbs: now they are inexcuſable, becauſe this vertue they haue in producing hearbs, is from God, who in the beginning did create hearbs and plants, without the helpe of ſtarres.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Did God create the Moone in the Full, or in the Change?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In the Full, becauſe God created his workes in perfection: now the moone is perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt in the Full. 2. Shee was ordained to illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the night, which ſhe doth moſt perfectly in the Full.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Haue the ſtarres their light wholy from the ſun?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: becauſe they haue different effects, therefore different light. 2. There is one glory of the ſun, and another of the moone, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother of the ſtarres, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why are the ſun and moone called great lights?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not in reſpect of quantity: for ſome ſtarres are greater: but becauſe they appeare to be greater. 2. In reſpect of their light, which is greater then the light of other ſtarres.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Of what figure is the heauen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:12378:15"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> Round: for this figure is moſt apt for moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 2. The Scripture witneſſeth the ſame, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many heauens are there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Philoſophers ſpeake of ten heauens, the Scriptures only of three, to the which, the former ten may bee reduced.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Shall the heauens be aboliſhed in the day of Iudgement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not in reſpect of their ſubſtance which is vncorruptible, but in reſpect of their moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, influence, and diuers operations in this inferiour world: for of theſe then there ſhall be no need, becauſe man ſhall bee tranſlated to a better life, and other liuing creatures ſhall be aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are the ſtarres innumerable?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not in themſelues: for they are naturall bodies, but in reſpect of our ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. 2. Theſe ſtarres of greater note are vnnumerable: for the <hi>Mathematicians</hi> haue reduced the 1022. ſtarres, to ſixe degrees of magnitude: for theſe of leſſer note are not numbred, becauſe not knowne.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is the ſun hot or cold?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Neither: but hee begets heat here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, becauſe of his great light, and not becauſe of his motion.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Haue the ſtarres life reaſonable, becauſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12378:16"/>
God is brought in ſpeaking to them in Scripture?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: if they had, they ſhould be capable of vertue and vice, life or death eternall. God is brought in, ſpeaking to them in Scriptures, &amp; ſo he is to inſenſible creatures, as the earth, ſeas, winde, &amp;c. to ſignifie our ſtupidity, which are duller to heare, and obey him, then ſenſles creatures.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Do the ſtarres moue of themſelues, as it ſeemeth by theſe places,</hi> Pſa. 19. Iob 9. Ioſ. 10. <hi>or are they moued by the ſpheres?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By their ſpheres: but the Scripture ſpeaketh rather of the ſtarrs then their ſpheres, becauſe the ſtarres are better knowne to vs, for the ſpheres we ſee not.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is the heauen and the earth corruptible or not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are incorruptible in regard of their ſubſtance: ſo witneſſeth the Scripture, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 1. and 3. <hi>chap. Pſal.</hi> 149. and therefore ſhall not be aboliſhed, but renewed to a more perfect ſtate: for the ſeruent deſire of the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature waiteth when the ſonnes of God ſhalbe reueald. Thoſe Scriptures that ſpeak of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the world, are to be vnderſtood of the alteration of ſome qualities to better.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Shall the ſun and other ſtarres moue as they do now, after the day of Iudgement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:12378:16"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for now they moue, to diſtinguiſh night and day, Summer and Winter: but then of theſe things there ſhall bee no need to man glorified.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How are the ſun and moone ſignes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are naturall ſignes of faire and foule weather, health and ſickenes, ſowing and mowing, &amp;c. and ſupernaturall ſignes of Gods wrath: for there ſhall be ſignes in the Sun, and Moone, and Starres, before the laſt day. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>Were the ſtarres made for ſignes to the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronomers, to fore-tell things to come?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They neither ſhould, nor can fore-tell by the ſtars. 1. They ſhould not, becauſe prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by the word of God, <hi>Iere.</hi> 10. <hi>Deu.</hi> 18. <hi>Leu.</hi> 20. ſecondly, condemned by the Canons, decrees and Councels of the Church, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Fathers. 3. They cannot foretell by theſe Scriptures, <hi>Eſay</hi> 41.44. and 47. <hi>Chap. Eccle.</hi> 8. and 10. <hi>Chap. Prou.</hi> 27. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. Again, the moſt part of, <hi>Apollos</hi> oracles were falſe, as witneſſeth <hi>Porphirius, lib. de oraculis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is this kind of Aſtrologie condemned?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it euerts Gods prouidence, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſheth the liberty of our will, makes all the myſteries of Chriſtian Religion to depend on the ſtarres; it is the cauſe of all villany and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12378:17"/>
neglect of Gods workes; yea, it makes all the miracles of the old and new teſtament, ſuch as the flood of <hi>Noah,</hi> the fire of <hi>Sodom,</hi> the birth, actions, and death of our Lord, to depend on the ſtarres.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Can the Aſtrologers foretell things to come by the ſtarres?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: becauſe they know not the forme, matter, motions, force and effects of the ſtarres in the things here below, they cannot explaine the hid cauſes, and properties of hearbs, ſtones, and liuing creatures: yea they know not what is doing now in other countries: and if they know not things preſent, much leſſe things to come.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But if they had the perfect knowledge of the ſtarres, could they not tell what is to come?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: becauſe wee cannot haue perfect knowledge of particular effects, except wee know their particular cauſes: now the ſtarres are but generall cauſes. 2. If this doctrine were true, then twinnes borne vnder the ſame ſtarre at the ſame time, ſhould bee of the ſame nature and diſpoſition: but this is falſe, as witneſſeth the birth of <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau.</hi> 3. It ſhould follow, that all thoſe that are killed in the warrs at the ſame time, ſhould bee borne at the ſame time: which is moſt falſe. 4. That all thoſe that liue
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12378:17"/>
according to the ſame lawes and religion, ſhould bee borne at the ſame time, vnder the ſame ſtarre. 5. That al the actions of mans free will, ſhould be knowne to them: which cannot be, ſeeing man can alter and change his will, when he lift. 6. If men could tell by the ſtarres what is to come, they ſhould bee had in great eſteeme: but it fares otherwiſe with them; for the greateſt, both Diuines and Philoſophers confute them, Kings and Magiſtrates con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne and puniſh them. 7. If they can tell what befalls to man, much more can they fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell what ſhall befall hearbs and trees, which are more ſubiect to the ſtarres then man: but this is falſe: for they cannot foretell how many Peares a Peare tree ſhal bring forth.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>Are not then the ſtarres naturall ſignes of things to come?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Naturall ſignes are rather the cauſes or effects of that they ſignifie, but the ſtarres are neither. 2. How can the ſtarres which are ſtill the ſame, be the ſignes of ſo many innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble accidents as fall out in the world? yet I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept Comets, which are not naturall ſtarres, but Meteors generated of naturall cauſes, yet they are ſupernaturall ſignes of things to come.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Can the Aſtrologers foretell nothing true?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:12378:18"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: oftentimes they fore-tell things truely, but that is not becauſe of the ſtarres, but by the inſtinct of Satan, with whom they haue commerce: and hee can foretell many things, partly, by Reuelation from God, and partly, becauſe he is a ſubtile ſpirk, and of long experience, and hee makes thoſe men foretell things to come, rather by mouing their phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies, or by dreames, or by offering to their eyes the ſhape, or to their eares the words of thoſe things he will foretell, or by characters. 2. They can foretell things to come, becauſe God permits them, for the greater deſtruction of thoſe that curiouſly conſult Sooth-ſayers: ſo he ſuffered <hi>Balaam</hi> &amp; his Aſſe to propheſie. 3. Men that are of ſubtile ſpirits, may foretell ſome things by looking diligently into the life, manners and diſpoſitions of men: as one may foretell, that a tyrant oppreſſing his ſubiects, ſhalbe killed. 4. They may foretell ſome things which may fall out true, becauſe of the creduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thoſe that conſult with them; for if they foretel good ſucceſſe to any, this ofttimes falls out, becauſe of the feruent deſire and vſing of all meanes to attaine the ſame: which doth fall out, not becauſe it was fore-told, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he to whom it was fore-told, vſed the meanes to haue it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:12378:18"/>Q. <hi>Is it not lawfull then to conſult with Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trologers and Sooth-ſayers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: becauſe in conſulting with them, we derogate from Gods glory, and honour them, in thinking that they can fore-tell all things; which is proper only to God. 2. If it bee vnlawfull to conuerſe with an excommunicate perſon, much leſſe ſhould we haue commerce with Satan, who is excommunicated from heauen to the place of darkeneſſe, and is the pernicious enemy of God and man.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whether are the beaſts or fiſhes perfecteſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The beaſts, becauſe they haue more perfect ſences, beget more perfect blood in our bodies, then fiſhes, haue more commerce with men, and are docible in many things; fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es are not.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why then were they created before the beaſts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As nature begins at that which is moſt imperfect in generation, ſo God in the creation did keepe this courſe: for man the little world and patterne of all the creatures, was not crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted till the ſixth day. 2. God keepeth that courſe in the 3. laſt dayes, which hee did in the 3. firſt: in the firſt he created heauen, and in the 4. did repleniſh it with ſtarres: the 2. hee made the ſeas, the 5. repleniſhed it with liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:12378:19"/>Q. <hi>Why ſpeaketh</hi> Moſes <hi>of the creation of ſome particular fiſhes, and not of trees and beaſts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe theſe fiſhes are greater then any earthly creatures, therefore we ſhould the more extoll Gods glory in conſidering them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How doe the waters bring forth the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The waters are not the efficient cauſe of the fiſhes, but the materiall, yet but in part, for fiſhes are compounded of the foure ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, notwithſtanding the waters are the predominant matter of the fiſhes, not in reſpect of their ſubſtance, for that is earth: but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of qualitie, moiſt and cold. Secondly, The temperature of the fiſhes are wateriſh. Thirdly, Water is the place of habitation, generation and conſeruation for the fiſhes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why were the birds created the fift day with the fiſhes, and not the ſixth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they were created of the water as the fiſhes. Secondly, Becauſe of the great reſemblance betweene the birds, and fiſhes, both in reſpect of their place, water and aire: for both theſe eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are perſpicuous, humid, moueable, and eaſie to be changed one into the other. Secondly, In reſpect of their bodies, for both are light and ſwift: the ſinnes of the fiſhes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12378:19"/>
anſwere to the birds wings, and their ſcales to birds feathers; they both want eares, paps, milke, bladder. Thirdly, Many kindes of birds dwell in the waters, as the Sea-meawes, Swans, &amp;c. Fourthly, their mouing is alike: for as the fiſhes ſwim, ſo the birds flie. Fiftly, They both vſe their tayle, to guide their flying and ſwimming.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Were the birds created of the water?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: but not of the thickeſt of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but rather of a watery vapour, betweene water and aire, therefore the birds conuerſe in the water and aire.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But it ſeemes the birds were created of the earth the ſixt day, by theſe words of the</hi> 2. <hi>Chapters</hi> (And the Lord hauing formed out of the ground euery beaſt of the field, and euery bird of the aire, brought them to <hi>Adam.</hi>)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> If God had created them the ſixt day of the ground, <hi>Moſes</hi> had not ſpoken of them the fift day. Secondly, in theſe words allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the coniunction <hi>(and)</hi> hath no reference to the word <hi>ground,</hi> as though both had bene formed of the <hi>ground:</hi> but to the word <hi>formed:</hi> ſo the meaning is, that not only the beaſts that were formed of the <hi>ground:</hi> but the birds alſo which God had created, were brought to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:12378:20"/>Q. <hi>How doth the earth bring forth liuing creatures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not actiuely, but paſſiuely: for the earth is not the efficient, but the materiall cauſe of earthly creatures.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What difference is there betweene the beaſt, cattel, and creeping thing?</hi> verſe 25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By <hi>behemah,</hi> in Hebrew, is vnderſtood the great beaſts, as <hi>Iob</hi> 40.15. By <hi>chaiah,</hi> the wild beaſts, in whom there is ſeen moſt liueli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: by <hi>remeſh,</hi> creeping things, ſuch as haue no feete at all, as ſerpents; and they that haue ſhort and little feete, as Ants.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did not God bleſſe the earthly crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as he did the fiſhes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. Moſes</hi> did omit this for breuities ſake. Secondly, the bleſſing of the fiſhes doth belong alſo to the beaſts. Thirdly, man is bleſſed, and in him the beaſts, as when hee was curſed, the earth was alſo, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. And when he was puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, the beaſts were puniſhed alſo, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was man particularly bleſſed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not only for multiplication: but alſo becauſe of the elect. And thirdly, becauſe mans copulation is oftentimes ſinfull, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinated</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Did God create in the beginning, imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect creatures, as Bees, Waſpes, and ſuch like?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:12378:20"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> He did not create them actually, as hee did the perfect creatures, but he created them in their cauſes, as hee gaue that faculty to the fleſh of an horſe, to beget Waſpes beeing dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Were Mules now created, or not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They were not Firſt, Becauſe they were found out by <hi>Anah, Geneſ.</hi> 36. Secondly, They are barren: but God created all creatures with his bleſſing to be fruitfull. &amp;c. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 1. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; this kinde of procreation is againſt nature, but God created euery thing according to his kinde, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 1. Fourthly, This is againſt his owne law, <hi>Leuit</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Who was man and the cattell created in the ſome day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, Becauſe they both dwell in the earth. Secondly, The earthly creatures are more familiar with man then others. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they are more profitable to man then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures. Fourthly, They are moſt like to man of all other creatures.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How doth Gods goodneſſe and wiſedom ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the creatures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Many wayes. Firſt, In the variety of ſo many thouſand diuers kindes of creatures. Secondly, In the comely order that is ſeene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. Thirdly, in that all things that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12378:21"/>
ſerue for the perfection of the world, is in the world; nothing can bee added, or impayred. Fourthly, In the ſympathy and concord that is amongſt ſome, and the diſcord and hatred that is amongſt others of the creatures. Fifthly, In the pulchritude and comelineſſe that is in euery creature, as may be ſeene in the body of man. Sixthly, In the admirable gouernment and adminiſtration of the world, in the which there is nothing ſo euill (whether it be naturall euill, as the defects of nature, or voluntary euill, ſuch as is the euill of puniſhment, and of ſin.) but al ſerues for the glory of God, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of this Vniuerſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is the power of God ſeene in the world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, By creating it of nothing. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, By ſuſtaining it with his power, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. Thirdly, By working many things miraculouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, aboue the courſe of nature; in which we ſee, that God doth not worke of neceſſity. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, He is not tyed to the ſecond cauſes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Could God haue made the world better then it is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, for his power is not limited: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee might haue made it ſooner then hee did, and larger, and fuller of Creatures.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was man the laſt of all the creatures created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:12378:21"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe God would make all things fit and prepared for him. Secondly, Becauſe he is the Lord and end of all other creatures. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Becauſe hee is moſt perfect: and in order of generation, that which is moſt perfect, is laſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherein did man exceed all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, In that hee had dominion ouer them all. Secondly, In that God prepared a moſt pleaſant place for man to dwell in, to wit, Paradiſe. Thirdly, Becauſe of his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and wit, in giuing names to the creatures according to their natures. Fourthly, In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his holineſſe and innocency. Fifthly, Becauſe hee was made immortall. Sixthly, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God tooke ſpecial care in the creating of man aboue the other creatures. Seuenthly, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the whole Trinity doth conſult about the making of man, as about a matter of great weight.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>Why ſpeaketh God in the plurall number,</hi> Let vs make man?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Here is the myſtery of the Trinity: for, the Father doth not here ſpeake to himſelfe, as the <hi>Iewes,</hi> nor to the Angels, as ſome hereticks thinke; but the Father ſpeaketh to the Son and holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:12378:22"/>Q. <hi>But how do we know that he ſpake not here to the Angels?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Eaſily: Becauſe the Angels cannot create neither ſoule nor body, for they are but creatures. Secondly, There is no mention in the Word that Angels created, but that God onely created man. Thirdly, Man was created according to Gods Image, and not according to the Similitude of Angels. Fourthly, God ſayes, <hi>To our Image:</hi> but the Image of God and Angels are not the ſame, but infinitely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was man onely created to the Image of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Image of God doth ſhine in euery creature in part, but in man moſt perfectly of all other creatures; for, he hath not onely exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and life, but alſo reaſon and wiſedome.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherein doth the Image of God conſiſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The image of God is moſt in the ſoule, which hath exiſtence: ſecondly, life; thirdly, ſence; fourthly, reaſon: againe, it is incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible; ſecondly, immortall; thirdly, it is indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with vnderſtanding, will and memorie: fourthly, it hath free will; fiftly, it is capable of wiſedome, grace and glorie; ſixtly, it hath power of all other creatures: in all which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the Image of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:12378:22"/>
               <hi>Q. Whether is the image of God moſt to be ſeene in Angels or men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In Angels, if wee reſpect their nature abſolutely: for they are of a more excellent nature than Man; but if we reſpect the dignity of Mans nature (the which is ſanctified and aſſumed by Ieſus the eſſentiall image of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,) the image of God is moſt to be ſeene in Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. If man be created to the Image of God, may he not be called the Image of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for Chriſt is onely the Image of God, becauſe hee is of that ſame nature with the Father, but Man is of another nature; and therefore, he is not the Image of God, but cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated to the Image of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is the Image of God ſeene in the woman as in the man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, equally in both, if we reſpect their nature; yet the Image of God is ſeene in man more perfectly; in reſpect that man is both the beginning and end of the woman. <hi>Et finis eſt praestantior finito.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Can the Image of God be aboliſhed by ſin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> If wee take his Image for that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe wherein <hi>Adam</hi> was created, then we ſay, that Gods Image was aboliſhed by ſinne; but if by the Image of God, wee vnderſtand
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12378:23"/>
mans reaſonable ſoule with the faculties ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, then his Image is not vtterly aboliſhed, but defaced by ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why did God create man to his Image?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, to manifeſt his ſingular loue and goodneſſe to Man: ſecondly, that all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures might reuerence Man the more, in that he carries the Image of God, as his badge and armes: thirdly, that Man might loue and ſerue God the more, for hee weares Gods Image as his Liuerie: fourthly, that Man might know the nature and properties of God more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly; for there is no creature wherein wee may contemplate the nature of God more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, than in our ſelues: fiftly, that God might haue ſome of his creatures with whom hee might be familiar, for his delight is with the ſonnes of men, <hi>Prouerbs</hi> 8. ſixtly, that man might be the more capable of eternall felicitie, and more aſſured of Gods loue: ſeuenthly, that Gods power might appeare the more, in that hee created ſuch an excellent piece of worke, at which all the creatures may admire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Had Man before his fall, dominion ouer the creatures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: <hi>Geneſis</hi> 1. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 8. ſecondly, he gaue names to them, in token of his power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them: thirdly, <hi>Euah</hi> conferred freely with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12378:23"/>
the Serpent, without feare: fourthly, it ſtood with the order of Nature, that ſome ſhould be ſuperiors, and ſome inferiors; and man was fitteſt to gouerne, becauſe of his <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Had man alſo dominion ouer the creatures after the Fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: <hi>Geneſis</hi> 9. ſecondly, becauſe wee kill them, and make them ſerue for our diuers vſes: thirdly, all kind of creatures were ſubiect to <hi>Noah</hi> in the Arke: fourthly, the Lions were familiar with <hi>Daniel,</hi> but mans dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them before the Fall, was naturall, this miraculous: ſecondly, that ſhould haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, this is but a while: thirdly, that did belong to all men, this onely to ſome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Should not man haue had rule ouer man in the ſtate of innocencie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: becauſe amongſt multitudes there can be no order, where ther are not ſome ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, and ſome inferiors: but the ſubiection of man to man then, had bin voluntary, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, ciuill, not ſeruile, and by conſtraint.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why then doth not God ſpeake of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of man ouer man, but of man ouer beaſts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the dominion of man ouer the beaſts, is a part of Gods Image, and did belong to all men, as men; but the dominion of man
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12378:24"/>
ouer man doth not agree to all, as they are man, but as wiſer, or better, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Should the wife haue beene ſubiect to the man in that ſtate of innocencie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: but this ſubiection of the wife ſhould not haue beene vnwilling, bitter, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome, as is it fell out afterward by ſinne.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Should mankinde haue beene multiplied by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nall copulation, as now?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: but without ſinne, for the ſoule and her faculties ſhould haue beene ſubiect to God, and the body to the ſoule; therfore God diſtinguiſhed in man, male and female: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, he ſaith, <hi>Increaſe and multiply:</hi> third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is ſaid, <hi>They ſhall be both in one fleſh:</hi> which is onely in reſpect of copulation.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Should man haue only eaten of the hearbs, and not alſo fleſh in Paradiſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Onely hearbs: firſt, becauſe Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion is onely extended to the hearbs: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the hearbs were moſt naturall and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple foode for that happy eſtate, and man was not made for food, but foode for man: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the hearbs were ſufficient, becauſe, before the earth was curſed, there was great ſtore of all ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of hearbs; and thoſe very powerfull, and good to feed man: but after the Fall, they loſt their force and former goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:12378:24"/>Q. <hi>Should the wilde beaſts, ſuch as Lions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fed on fleſh, before the Fall, as they do now?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: but on the hearbs onely: firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe heere is no fleſh mentioned, but onely hearbs: ſecondly, if it had bene permitted to them to eate fleſh before the Floud, then thoſe rauening beaſts that were in the Arke, ſhould haue eat fleſh: but in the Arke there was no fleſh for them: therefore they did feed on the hearbs.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How comes it now, that theſe kind of beaſts do not feed on hearbs now, but on fleſh?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the earth doth not yeeld ſuch comfortable and nouriſhing hearbs as then: ſecondly, the temperature of the creature is not ſo ſound now as it was before the Floud.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is it vnderſtood, that all which God made, was very good?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All things were good: firſt, in reſpect of their ſubſtance which is vnchangeable: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, in reſpect of their perfect eſtate they were created in: thirdly, in reſpect of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents or properties: fourthly, becauſe of their operations, which brought forth perfect effects.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did not God ſee that all things were very good, till man was created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe man is the end of all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12378:25"/>
ſecondly, in him, as in a little world, are to be ſeene all the creatures: thirdly, becauſe Chriſt, who is eſſentiall goodneſſe, was to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie the nature of man, in taking vpon him his fleſh.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>Questions on the ſecond Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. DId God create the world at the ſame inſtant, or in the ſpace of ſixe dayes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In the ſpace of ſixe dayes: firſt, becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> narration is hiſtoricall, and therefore he ſpeaketh of ſixe diſtinct dayes: ſecondly, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Exodus</hi> 20. and 31. vrgeth the Iewes to worke ſixe dayes, and reſt the ſeuenth, becauſe God created the world in ſixe daies, and reſted the ſeuenth: this reaſon had beene ridiculous, if GOD had made the world in an inſtant: thirdly, if wee vnderſtand <hi>Moſes</hi> in this place allegorically, then wee muſt make this whole hiſtorie an allegorie: fourthly, if the ſeuenth day had beene the firſt (and in it God had cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated the world) then how is it vnderſtood that God reſted the ſeuenth day? fiftly, how could ſo many diuers kindes of creatures be created in the ſame inſtant of time? yea then we muſt ſay, that man was created and brought into
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12378:25"/>
Paradiſe, and was caſt aſleepe, and <hi>Euah</hi> was formed of his rib the ſame inſtant.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How then it that vnderſtood,</hi> Eccleſiaſt. 18. <hi>He that liueth for euer, created all things to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is to be vnderſtood of that confuſed maſſe that God created in the beginning: out of the which afterward hee created the reſt of the creatures in their diſtinct dayes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did God ſpend ſo much time in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not becauſe he was weake, and could not make it in leſſe time, but that we might the more ſeriouſly conſider the order of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, diſtinction and repleniſhing of the world; and in theſe, the omnipotencie, wiſedome and goodneſſe of God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Did God make the world of neceſſitie, or of his owne accord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Of his owne free will, becauſe he made it at that time and manner he thought fitteſt: ſecondly, becauſe he, in crea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, wrought o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than the courſe of Nature doth; for he made the heauens without light, then made light: firſt, imperfect; afterward, perfect: and he made the hearbs before the Sunne.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Can it be ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hered from hence, that as God created the world in ſixe dayes, and reſted the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12378:26"/>
ſo likewiſe the world ſhall continue ſixe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or ſixe thouſand yeeres, and after ſhall be a perpetuall Sabbath?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for this computation is but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture, or fiction of <hi>Elias,</hi> not the Prophet, but the Rabbin, hauing no ground. Secondly, If this were true, we ſhould know how long the world ſhould continue, and fully know the time of Chriſts comming: which cannot bee: for his comming ſhalbe as a theef in the night, as Lightning; his comming ſhall bee as the comming of the flood: of this houre knoweth no man, not the Angels; the Father hath put in his owne power the times and ſeaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Were the Angels created, or are they eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Created, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 4. &amp; 10. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1. The Church confeſſeth; the Fathers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme; and generall Councel, eſtabliſh this point. Secondly, Onely God is eternall Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, They are parts of the world, therefore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are the Angels reall ſubſtances, or onely good and bad motions in the minde, as though the Sadduces?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are indiuiduall ſubſtances. Firſt, Their names doe ſhew this, for they are called Meſſengers, Watchmen, &amp;c. Secondly, Their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12378:26"/>
actions and operations, which onely belong to perſonall ſubſtances: for, they ſerue God; come to vs; comfort vs; gather together the Elect; an Angell wreſtled with <hi>Iaacob;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred with <hi>Abraham;</hi> they were receiued by <hi>Lot;</hi> &amp;c. Angels declared Chriſts Natiuity to the ſhepheards, his Reſurrection to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Thirdly, Some of them ſtood, ſome fell, therefore ſubſtances. Fourthly, We ſhall bee like them: <hi>Ergo,</hi> they are not bare motions.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is meant here by the Hoſt of Heauen and earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By thoſe of Heauen, is meant the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, for they are called the heauenly hoſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. alſo the Stars, <hi>Eſay</hi> 34. Therefore <hi>the Stars in their courſes fought againſt Siſera, Iudges</hi> 5. By the hoſt of Earth, is meant all the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly creatures: therefore God is called the Lord of hoſtes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Were the Angels created before this viſible world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: becauſe God created all things in the beginning: <hi>ergo,</hi> Angels, and not before, or elſe this had beene no beginning. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, They were created for the vſe of man, but man was not before the beginning: <hi>ergo,</hi> not Angels.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Were they created after the ſixe dayes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:12378:27"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for God reſted from all his worke the ſeuenth day.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Then what day were they created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The firſt, that they might bee the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders and admirers of Gods power and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in creating the World. Secondly, They are called Angels of Heauen in Scripture; not onely becauſe they inhabit, but alſo becauſe they were created with the heauen the firſt day. Thirdly, This is manifeſt in <hi>Iob</hi> 38. where it is ſayd, that the Sonnes of God (that is, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels) did ſing and ſhowte when God laid the foundations of the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Where were they created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In Heauen: for ſome of them fell from thence; And Chriſt ſaw Satan like Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fall from Heauen: therefore they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Hoſt and Angels of Heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why doth not</hi> Moſes <hi>ſpeake diſtinctly of the creation of Angels?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe he did accomodate himſelfe to the rude capacity of the <hi>Iewes;</hi> therefore hee doth onely ſpeake here of the creation of viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble creatures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is meant by Gods reſt on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day? was he weary?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: but by his reſt, is vnderſtood his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting and ceaſing to make other creatures.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:12378:27"/>Q. <hi>Did God reſt from all his workes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, of creation, but not of preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for yet the Father worketh with the Son, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Did God create no other creatures ſince the Creation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for whatſoeuer ſeemes to be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated ſince, it was created before, either in the matter thereof (as Wormes, Flies, Bees, and ſuch like) or elſe, in that God gaue faculty to ſome creatures of diuers kindes, to produce a third kinde, as Mules of the Horſe and Aſſe; &amp; power he gaue to the Starres, to produce ſome creatures of putrified matter: yet ſome crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures he doth ſtill produce, either by generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as all particular men, and other creatures that are generated, or by creation, either ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, as the ſoules of men, or extraordinary, as the Starre that appeared to the Wiſe men, and the Doue that deſcended on Chriſt: ſo then God reſted from creating new kindes of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but not from producing the indiuiduall creatures, of thoſe kinds that were made in the Beginning.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is it ſayd here that God ended his worke the ſeuenth day, ſeeing they were ended the ſixth day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The creatures were perfected the ſixth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12378:28"/>
day, in reſpect of their ſubſtance, qualities, and properties; but in reſpect of their operation, they were not perfected till the ſeuenth day: for they did not beginne to produce effects till after the ſixth day: and ſeeing operation is the end of the forme, they were not fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected till they began to worke.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How do you vnderſtand that God ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Sabbath?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In that he ſeparated it from the other dayes, and conſecrated it for holy vſes, hee would haue this to bee a Day of reſt, and wherein we might wholy addict our ſelues for his ſeruice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Did God inioyne</hi> Adam <hi>to keepe this day holy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: but this was afterwards comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Moſes:</hi> for in that happy eſtate it had not bin needfull to appoint one day for Gods ſeruice, ſeeing euery day ſhould haue bene a day of reſt, and Sabbath for <hi>Adam</hi> to meditate on Gods workes. Secondly, it was not need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for man then to reſt from ſeruill workes, becauſe in that happineſſe, mans labour ſhould not haue bene wearyſome. Thirdly, wee read of no commandement that was giuen to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam:</hi> but only one, concerning not eating the forbidden fruite. Fourthly, if this law had
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12378:28"/>
bene giuen to <hi>Adam,</hi> it ſhould haue tied all his poſterity to the obſeruation thereof: but wee do not read, that any one of the Fathers before <hi>Moſes,</hi> did obſerue the Sabbath. Fiftly, if the Sabbath had bene kept by the Fathers, <hi>Moſes</hi> would haue mentioned the ſame, as a ſtrong argument to perſwade the Iewes to keepe it. Sixtly, the ſoundeſt of the Fathers are of this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is meant here by the day wherein God made the heauen and the earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the day is meant, the whole 6. daies: ſo, often in the Scriptures day ſignifieth time, as the day of ſaluation, the day of iudgement.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is meant by a mist that watred the earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not a fountaine: but a vapour, which is the matter of raine.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is meant by this, that God made man of the duſt of the earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By man is vnderſtood his body: by duſt, the matter of his body, to put vs in minde of humility, and of this bodies frailty: by earth, is vnderſtood the 4 elements: for man is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly compoſed of all: but earth is only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, becauſe in mans body there is more earth then any other element. Secondly, when man dies, his body is reſolued into earth.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12378:29"/>
Thirdly, he liues vpon the earth. Fourthly, he taketh his clothes and food from the earth.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was not the body of man rather made of heauenly then earthly ſubſtance, ſeeing the ſoule is ſo excellent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the ſoule of man did require ſuch a body as was capable of ſenſes, by the which as by inſtruments ſhee might worke in the body: but the celeſtiall bodies are not capable of ſenſes: for they are not capable of the firſt qualities.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherein doth the body of man exceed the bodies of other creatures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, in that the body of man is made ſtraight: that he may behold heauen his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, that his ſenſes might vſe their function the better, his hands might bee imployed in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, not in walking. Secondly, in that his ſenſes are more perfect then of other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, not in the quicker apprehenſion of the ſenſible obiect: for other creatures haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecter ſenſes in this regard: but that man can diſcerne more perfecter by his ſenſes, the differences of obiects then other creatures. Thirdly, in that mans body is more perfectly compounded of the 4. elements, then other bodies: for the bodies of the creatures are more earthly, or more wateriſh.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:12378:29"/>Q. <hi>Of what age created God</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eua?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In the prime and flowre of their age. Firſt, becauſe God created all things in their perfect eſtate. Secondly, becauſe God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to increaſe and multiply, which they could not haue done, if they had not bin created of a ripe age.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whether was the body or the ſoule of man created firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The body: for God did keepe the ſame courſe in mans creation, which nature doth now in mans generation: for firſt, the body is formed in the mothers wombe, and then the ſoule is infuſed.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is the creation of mans ſoule called a breathing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, to ſhew vs that the ſoule was not taken out of the power of the matter: but was created of nothing, and infuſed in the body. Secondly, to teach vs Gods power, who did as eaſily create the ſoule, as man doth breathe. Thirdly, to ſhew the excellency of mans ſoule, which ſeemeth as it were the breath of Gods owne mouth.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is the ſoule of man, of the eſſence of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: if it were, it ſhould bee either a part thereof, or the whole: it is not a part; for Gods
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12378:30"/>
eſſence cannot be deuided in parts, neither is it the whole: for then all men ſhould be but one ſoule. Secondly, if mans ſoule were a part of Gods eſſence, then a part of Gods eſſence ſhould be ſinfull, and ſubiect to the wrath of God, and paines of hell.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did God breathe the ſoule, rather in the face, then in any other part of man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe, in the face are all the ſenſes, which are the organs of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why in the noſthrils rather than in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of the face?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To teach vs, that hee is the only author of our breathing: ſecondly, to ſhew the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our life, which dependeth from the noſthrils: thirdly, becauſe the noſe is the moſt commodious inſtrument of breathing, by which the ſoule is kept in the body.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Did God create one ſoule in man, or three?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Only one: firſt, bicauſe one body can haue but one eſſentiall forme: ſecondly, the power of growing, feeling &amp; reaſoning, are not three ſoules, but three faculties of one ſoule: thirdly, the Scripture neuer ſpeakes but of one ſoule.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Were the ſoules of men created long before the body, as thought</hi> Plato <hi>and</hi> Origines?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for God created all things perfect, but the ſoule of man, being a part of man;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12378:30"/>
without, the body could not be perfect<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, now in generation the body is no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner formed, but God infuſeth the ſoule; the ſame order did God keepe in mans creation: thirdly, the ſoules in all that time ſhould haue either done good or euill: but <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> did neither good nor euill before they were borne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Seeing the ſoule doth exist, after the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, why did ſhe not exiſt before the creation of the body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Shee doth exiſt after the diſſolution of the body, of neceſſitie, being immortall: but it was not fit ſhe ſhould exiſt, before the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the body, ſeeing ſhe is the natural forme, and eſſentiall part of man.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whether are the ſoules of men infuſed in the bodies, or are they deriued and propagated one of another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By creating they are infuſed, and by infuſing created: for mans ſoule being incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall and indiuiſible, cannot be propagated of any other ſoule, nor multiplied, that is plaine by <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.1. and <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 12.7.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is the ſoule of man immortall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is: becauſe a ſimple eſſence voyde of contrarieties, and bodily accidents: ſecondly, It is created to Gods Image: and mans ſoule
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12378:31"/>
is not like God, only in that it is capable of all ſciences, and in that it hath an appetite infinite, which cannot be filled, but with God; and that it hath a will free and indifferent to all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular good: but alſo in that deſire which it hath of immortalitie: thirdly, man hath do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer the creatures, which conſiſteth alſo in this, that his ſoule is immortall, theirs are not: fourthly, Mans ſoule is not produced of any matter by generation, but is induced in the body by creation, the ſoules of all other creatures were procreated of the Elements, for the earth brings out beaſts; and the waters fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes: this is alſo manifeſt by many places of Scripture.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is the ſoule of man immortall by nature, or by grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Internally: that is, as it is a ſimple im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>materiall ſubſtance, it is immortall by nature: but externally, as it depends on God, hath it being and ſubſiſtance in him, it is immortall by grace.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In what place of the world was Paradiſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not in any other earth ſeparated from ours, by the Ocean; nor higher than the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme region of the ayre, as ſome Fathers thought: but in <hi>Meſopotamia</hi> and the borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring countries to it: for Paradiſe was planted
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12378:31"/>
on the Eaſt ſide of <hi>Eden,</hi> which is in <hi>Meſopota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia:</hi> ſecondly, that is manifeſt by the Riuers <hi>Tigris</hi> and <hi>Euphrates,</hi> which ſpring out of the mountaines of <hi>Armenia,</hi> and flow tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the countries of <hi>Meſopotamia, Aſſyria</hi> and <hi>Chaldea,</hi> and runne into the <hi>Perſian</hi> gulph, and theſe are the Riuers of Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Should man haue remayned in Paradiſe onely, if he had not ſinned?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for Paradiſe was not ſo large as to containe all mankinde, being comprehended within the limits of theſe countries aforeſayd: ſecondly, man had power ouer the whole earth; and all the hearbs of the ground were giuen to him for foode; and therefore hee was to repleniſh the whole earth: thirdly, how ſhould the earth be trimmed, manured and made fruitfull, if man had dwelt in Paradiſe?</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Then to what end did God make Paradiſe, ſeeing he knew that man ſhould preſently fall, and be cast out of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He made it, that <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo long as hee obeyed God, might enioy it: ſecondly, that it might be a figure and type of the heauenly Paradiſe, and ioyes of the life to come: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to put him in mind, after his fall, what great bleſſings he had loſt, by loſing Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is Paradiſe yet extant, or not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:12378:32"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is not extant: for <hi>Paradiſe</hi> was in theſe Countries of <hi>Meſopotamia, Aſſyria, &amp;c.</hi> through the which <hi>Tigris</hi> and <hi>Euphrates</hi> (the Riuers of <hi>Paradiſe</hi>) did flowe: but thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries are ſtill populous, and no ſigne now of <hi>Paradiſe:</hi> ſecondly, the Floud, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 7. was fifteene cubites higher then the mountaines, therefore it was alſo defaced with the floud.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was the tree of life called ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it was the ſacrament or ſigne of life, both naturall in Paradiſe, and ſpirituall in heauen: or as ſome think, becauſe it had power, being eaten, to preſerue the life of man a long time, but not for euer: for man was not to liue ſtill a naturall life. Againe, the body of man was corruptible, becauſe it was made of matter the ſubiect of corruption, of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements and parts; as alſo becauſe the naturall heate of the body, by degrees is extenuated, and the radicall humor exhauſted: and in theſe reſpects, although this tree had that vertue to preſerue the life of the body a long time, yet not for euer.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did God forbid man to eate of the tree of knowledge of good and euill?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not becauſe it was euill in it ſelfe, or hurtfull to man: but becauſe by this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, God would try mans obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:12378:32"/>Q. <hi>Why was the tree, called the tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good and euill?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not becauſe it had power either to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get knowledge in <hi>Adam,</hi> or to augment his knowledge, as the Hebrewes and <hi>Ioſephus</hi> do thinke: for <hi>Adam</hi> was created with perfect knowledge: neither can corporall fruits pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſpirituall effects in the ſoule: but it was ſo named from the euent: for man knew now what was good and euill by experience, hauing tranſgreſſed in eating of this tree. Secondly, it was ſo named, becauſe of Satans falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, who intiſed them to eate of it, promiſing they ſhould be as Gods, knowing good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What riuers were thoſe, that</hi> Moſes <hi>calls here</hi> Phiſon, <hi>and</hi> Gehon?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They were parts of <hi>Tigris,</hi> and <hi>Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> which riuer is ſometimes named one, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they flow together, and are ioyned in one below <hi>Babylon:</hi> ſometimes two, in reſpect of the place, from whence they ſpring and where they end. Sometimes foure, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their foure heads, whereof, two ſpring out of the mountaines, and other two emptie themſelues in the <hi>Perſian</hi> ſea.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Then</hi> Phiſon <hi>is not</hi> Ganges <hi>of</hi> India, <hi>nor</hi> Gehon, Nilus <hi>of</hi> Egypt?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:12378:33"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for <hi>Ganges</hi> ſpringeth out of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſus</hi> of <hi>India, Nilus</hi> out of the mountaine of inferior <hi>Mauritania:</hi> but <hi>Phiſon</hi> and <hi>Geho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> out of <hi>Armenia: Nilus</hi> exonerateth her ſelfe in the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> ſea: but <hi>Phiſon</hi> and <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hon</hi> into the Perſian Gulfe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What country is this</hi> Hauilah?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not a country in <hi>India,</hi> but bordering vpon <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> and <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> as may be gathered out of <hi>Gene. Chap.</hi> 25.18.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is</hi> Bdellium?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is a blacke tree, the bigneſſe of an Oliue tree, from the which there runneth a kind of ſweete gum. <hi>Plinius. lib.</hi> 12. <hi>Chapt.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is that vnderſtood, that God did put</hi> Adam <hi>into the garden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Either by the inward perſwaſion of God hee was led thither, as Chriſt was led to the wilderneſſe, <hi>Math.</hi> 4. or he was caught by the Spirit, as <hi>Henoch, Habbacuc,</hi> and <hi>Philip,</hi> or elſe by an Angell, in the ſhape of man, he was led to Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did not God create</hi> Adam <hi>in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To let him know that Paradiſe did not belong to him by nature, but by grace. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, to teach him to bee the more circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in obeying God, conſidering hee might
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12378:33"/>
be as well put out of it, as hee was brought in, if he brake Gods Law. Thirdly, that hee ſhould haue no cauſe to accuſe God of cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in putting him out of that place, which by nature was due to him; therefore hee returnes to the place from whence he came.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Then why was</hi> Euah <hi>created in Paradiſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Adam,</hi> out of whoſe ſide ſhee was taken, was now in Paradiſe. Secondly, ſhe is not now properly created, but formed and framed out of <hi>Adams</hi> rib: for when <hi>Adam</hi> was formed, ſhe was created <hi>potentia</hi> in him, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the body of <hi>Adam</hi> was the matter of her body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Should man haue wrought in Paradiſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: but not for need, and with trouble as now: but with pleaſure, to keepe himſelfe from idlenes. Secondly, thereby to ſtirre him vp the more to contemplate heauenly things. And thirdly, to try the diuers natures of grounds, and of thoſe things that grow on the ground.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Doth theſe words,</hi> You ſhall eate of euery tree of the garden, <hi>containe a precept or a permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not a precept, but a permiſſion: for if God did command <hi>Adam</hi> to eate of euery tree, he ſhould haue bene tied to it. Secondly,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12378:34"/>
man hath no need to be commanded to eate, when he is hungry: for hee can do that by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Thirdly, he knew that all the trees were created to that vſe, therefore he needs no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement to eate.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was this commandement of not eating the tree of Knowledge of good and euill, inioyned to</hi> Eua <hi>alſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Yes: for ſo ſhee confeſſed to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. Secondly, If ſhe had not beene comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to abſtaine from it, ſhee ſhould not haue ſinned in eating of it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How could this precept belong to</hi> Eua, <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe was not yet created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It was firſt giuen to <hi>Adam,</hi> and then by <hi>Adam</hi> it was deliuered to <hi>Eua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did God forbid</hi> Adam <hi>to eate of this tree?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, To let him know, that he was but a creature and ſeruant, and therfore had a Lord whom he muſt ſerue and obey. Secondly, To let him ſee, that hee had free will and power both to chuſe and refuſe any thing he pleaſed. Thirdly, To exerciſe him in obedience.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But ſeeing God knew that</hi> Adam <hi>would violate this precept, &amp; bring himſelfe &amp; his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to perpetuall miſery, why would God inioyne it to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:12378:34"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> To make him inexcuſable: for he made him vpright, and gaue him grace to obey, if he would: <hi>dedit Adamo poſſe, ſi vellet; non, et velle, et poſſe.</hi> Secondly, Although God knew that man would ſinne, yet hee did permit him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was to conuert that ſinne of <hi>Adam</hi> to his greater good, in ſending his Sonne into the world. Thirdly, hee ſuffered him to fall, that his mercy and iuſtice might appeare the more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How is it vnderſtood, that whatſoeuer day</hi> Adam <hi>ſhould eate of the Forbidden tree, he ſhould die?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He did not dye actually, as ſoone as he had eaten the forbidden fruite, but now he was ſubiect to death, and the neceſſity of dying is layd vpon him. Secondly, hee may be ſayd to dye actually that day, becauſe then the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of body &amp; ſoule, which are the fore-ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners &amp; cauſes of death actual, did ſeaze vpon him: &amp; ſo <hi>mortuus eſt morte inchoata, ſed non completa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why did not God expreſſely threaten</hi> Adam <hi>with death eternall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe God in the old Teſtament ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth but ſparingly of death eternall and vnder ſhaddowes. Secondly, death corporal is better knowne to man (not onely by faith and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but alſo by experience) then death eternal,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12378:35"/>
which onely is knowne by faith. Thirdly, hee would ſpeake of ſuch a death, as did not onely belong vnto him, but to all his poſterity, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they did repent: and this is the death of the body, whereof all are partakers.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did God threaten</hi> Adam <hi>with death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe death is the greateſt and moſt fearefull miſery that can happen to man. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, The name of death comprehends all the miſeries and afflictions that doe befall man in this life, becauſe they are preparations to death: <hi>Nam vt via ad generationem eſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratio, ſic via ad interitum eſt mors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Then what death is meant here?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Both of body and ſoule, temporall and eternall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How can death corporall bee a puniſhment for ſinne, ſeeing it proceeds of naturall cauſes, as of contrary qualities?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is not the puniſhment of ſinne, as it proceedes of naturall cauſes, but in reſpect that God ordayned <hi>Adam</hi> to liue immortally, if he had not ſinned: now hauing ſinned, death fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes as the ſtipend of ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why was it not good that man ſhould bee alone?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe man without the woman could not procreate children, and ſo man-kinde
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12378:35"/>
could not bee multiplyed. Secondly, Chriſt could not haue come in the fleſh. Thirdly, The Elect and Church of God could not haue increaſed, if <hi>Adam</hi> had beene alone.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How were the creatures brought to</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Either by the helpe of Angels, or by that naturall inſtinct which the Greekes call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by the which euery creature perceiueth what is good and bad for them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did God bring the creatures to</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, To let him ſee how much hee did excel them, and how much the more he ſhould be thankefull. Secondly, Becauſe hee was the Lord of the beaſts, God would haue him to ſee his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Thirdly, that he might name them. Fourthly, That poſterity might know, what excellent knowledge <hi>Adam</hi> had, in giuing names to the creatures according to their kindes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why were not the fiſhes brought to</hi> Adam?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they doe not ſo much reſemble man as the beaſts: ſecondly, becauſe they could not be ſuch a help to man as the beaſts: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe they could not liue out of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Had</hi> Adam <hi>the knowledge of all things, as
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12378:36"/>
ſeene as he was created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, becauſe he was created perfect, as well in regard of the gifts of his minde, as of his body: ſecondly, he was to be the Father, Teacher, and Gouernour of mankinde, which he could not haue beene without excellent knowledge: thirdly, knowledge was a part of <hi>Adams</hi> happineſſe, and hee could not haue beene perfectly happy, if he had beene at any time ignorant: fourthly, if God prepared food and all things needful for his body; then much more, ſcience and vnderſtanding, which is the food of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Should</hi> Adams <hi>Poſterity, in the ſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, haue knowledge ingrafted in them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out labour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for it is naturall to man to attaine to knowledge by his ſenſes and experience, therefore the ſoule hath receiued a body with ſenſes, which the ſoule may vſe as organs, to beget knowledge; yet man in that happy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate ſhould haue attained to knowledge ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and with greater eaſe than now, becauſe the wit was moſt excellent, the ſenſes more perfect, the life longer, the body healthier and ſtronger, and there ſhould haue beene no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment to learning as now.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Had</hi> Adam <hi>the knowledge of ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12378:36"/>
things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, or elſe his knowledge had not bin perfect: ſecondly, without this knowledge he could not haue knowne God, nor the Angels, nor the end of his owne creation.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Had</hi> Adam <hi>more wiſedome than any man euer ſince?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: except Chriſt. And <hi>Adams</hi> wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome did excell ours: firſt, in that he knew all naturall things, we but ſome: ſecondly, his knowledge did proceed of the cauſes of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall things, but ours from the effects: thirdly, his knowledge could not be loſt, but ours is often; partly through the infirmity and corruption of our naturall ſenſes, partly by idleneſſe and ceaſing to ſtudy; and partly by the contrary habit of ignorance and falſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Had</hi> Adam <hi>the knowledge of the heauens, and their operations, as he had of earthly creatures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, becauſe his minde was perfect; and knowledge is the perfection of the minde: ſecondly, the power, wiſedome and prouidence of God is ſeene in the heauenly bodies as in the earthly: thirdly, <hi>Adam</hi> could not haue had the perfect knowledge of earthly things, if hee had not had the knowledge of heauenly: for the knowledge of the earthly things, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12378:37"/>
from the knowledge of the heauenly.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What were the effects of that originall righteouſneſſe, in the which</hi> Adam <hi>was created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The effects thereof are many, eſpecially theſe foure: firſt, the holineſſe of his will and reaſon, which was wholy ſubiect to God: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the vprightneſſe of the inferiour part, that is, of the fleſh and ſenſes, which were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly obedient to the ſuperiour part of the ſoule: thirdly, perfect inclination to do good, and eſchew euill: fourthly, a perpetuall ioy of the minde, and peace of conſcience, ariſing from this holineſſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Hath Chriſt brought vs more happineſſe by his Incarnation, than</hi> Adam <hi>loſt by his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: for although ſinne did abound, yet grace did more abound, as the Apoſtle diſputeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. Therefore, <hi>Foelix fuit Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> culpa cuius delenda cauſa, tantum habemus R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregorius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was</hi> Adam <hi>mortall or immortall befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He was immortall, not ſimply, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally, if he did obey God, if not, then he ſhould die.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How was he immortall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not as God, who is altogether immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12378:37"/>
both internally and externally, becauſe in him there is no mutability: nor as the Angels, who are immortal, becauſe they are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of a matter, which is the ſubiect of corruption: nor as the heauens, which though they haue a materiall ſubſtance, yet this is not the ſubiect of contradiction &amp; contrary qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, as the ſublunary and elementall bodies are: but <hi>Hdam</hi> was immortall by grace, and the power of God, who would haue preſerued him ſupernaturally from corruption, although naturally he was ſubiect to corruption.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Then this gift of immortality which</hi> Adam <hi>ſhould haue inioyed, was not naturally due to him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for if it had bin naturall, it ſhould not haue bin taken from <hi>Adam:</hi> but ſinne did neither aboliſh nor diminiſh mans naturall gifts. Secondly, that which is againſt nature, cannot be due to nature: but for the body to be immortall, is againſt the nature of mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſeeing it is compounded of contrary quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why would God forme</hi> Eua <hi>of</hi> Adam <hi>ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould not feele any paine in loſing his rib. Secondly, to ſignifie a great myſterie: for as <hi>Eua</hi> was formed out of the ſide of <hi>Adam</hi> ſleeping: ſo the Church was reformed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12378:38"/>
by water and blood, out of the body of Chriſt dying.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was</hi> Eua <hi>made rather of the ſide, then of any other part of the body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the ſide is the middle of the body<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſignifie that the woman muſt bee of equall dignity with the man, therefore ſhe was not made of the head, nor of the foote, for ſhe muſt neither be ſuperior, nor inferior to him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Of what ſide was ſhe taken out?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is probable, that ſhee was taken out of the left ſide, for the heart inclineth to that ſide: ſo man and women ſhould imbrace each other with hearty loue. And as the left ſide is weakeſt, ſo is the woman the weaker veſſell: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the males are conceiued in the right ſide, the females in the left; and as the ſides are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by the armes, ſo muſt the woman by the husband.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was</hi> Eua <hi>made of the man, and not of the earth, as</hi> Adam <hi>was?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould loue his wife the more, not only becauſe ſhe is of that ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with him, that ſhee is ioyned with him by carnall copulation, that ſhee doth bring him forth children: but alſo becauſe ſhee is a part of his owne ſubſtance. Secondly, <hi>Eua</hi> was made of <hi>Adam,</hi> to ſhew that <hi>Adam</hi> is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12378:38"/>
of the woman, and of all mankind. Thirdly, that we might learne from hence, that myſticall coniunction betwixt Chriſt and his Church.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is meant by the rib?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not the bare bone: but bone with the fleſh thereof, as <hi>Adam</hi> teſtifieth: <hi>Thou art bone of my bone, and fleſh of my fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How did God of one rib make a whole wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Either by rarefaction, or multiplication of the ſame rib, or by ſome addition of ſome new matter: as Chriſt did feed 5. thouſand men with 5. loaues: for God can of nothing, or of euery thing make any thing.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was this rib, whereof</hi> Eua <hi>was created, one of</hi> Adams <hi>naturall ribs, or was it a ſuperfluous rib?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It was one of <hi>Adams</hi> naturall ribs: for how elſe could hee haue ſayd of <hi>Eua, Thou art bone of my bone?</hi> or how could <hi>Eua</hi> be ſayd, to be formed of <hi>Adam?</hi> Neither was <hi>Adam</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, although he wanted his rib: for God did fill vp that place with fleſh.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If</hi> Adam <hi>loſt one of his ribs, how comes it, that the poſterity of</hi> Adam <hi>haue all their</hi> 24. <hi>ribs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Although <hi>Abraham</hi> was circumciſed: yet he begot his children vncircumciſed; and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12378:39"/>
a retained man doth beget a whole man: for nature, if ſhe be not hindred, retaines her owne force and vigor, and brings forth the perfecteſt effects ſhe can.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How came it, that</hi> Adam, <hi>in loſing his rib, did not feele paine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Eyther in regard of his deepeſleepe, <hi>for thoſe that are in a lethargie, doe feele neither ſtripes nor wounds;</hi> or elſe, becauſe God did ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, and hinder the act of feeling, which is in the nerues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why doth not</hi> Moſes <hi>ſpeake as well of the creation of</hi> Eua's <hi>ſoule, as of her body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe her body was otherwiſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then the body of <hi>Adam:</hi> but the manner of the creation of her ſoule, is all one with that of <hi>Adams,</hi> therefore there was no need of repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was</hi> Eua <hi>brought to</hi> Adam?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſignifie, that ſhee was <hi>Adams</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion. Secondly, a helpe to him to beget chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Thirdly, that the man is not for the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but the woman for the man. Fourthly, this bringing ſignifieth, that they are now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted and married.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Had</hi> Eua <hi>a reaſonable ſoule as</hi> Adam <hi>bad?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: becauſe ſhe was made for a helpe to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12378:39"/>
man, which ſhee could not haue bin without a reaſonable ſoule: ſecondly, both receiue a Law, vpon both was inflicted puniſhment for the breach thereof; both their bodies are alike: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption is promiſed too both; and both doe expect glory.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did not God create</hi> Eua <hi>as ſoon as</hi> Adam?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That <hi>Adam</hi> liuing a priuate life a while, might the better perceiue the comforts of the married life. Secondly, that hee might loue God the more, who prouided ſuch a comfort to him, when he was alone.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is man and woman of the ſame kind?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: for male &amp; female make no eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all difference. Secondly, if they were not of the ſame kind, how could they procreate children? Thirdly, they both haue the ſame definition and eſſentiall properties. Fourthly, wee read that maids haue become boyes, which could not be, if they were of diuers kinds, <hi>Plinius lib</hi> 7. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Gellius. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How could</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eua <hi>bee married, ſeeing they were ſo neere a kin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The neereneſſe of kin, which forbiddeth matrimony, is that which ariſeth of carnall copulation, and <hi>Eua</hi> was not begotten, but cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated of <hi>Adam:</hi> therefore ſhe was not his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but his wife.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was there but one woman created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:12378:40"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe that one woman is ſufficient to bee a helpe to one man. Secondly, to teach poſterity, that God doth hate Polygamy. Thirdly, that the loue of man might bee the greater to his wife.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is man and woman one fleſh?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they are ioyned together to liue one common life. Secondly, in reſpect of their carnall copulation. Thirdly, in reſpect of procreation of one fleſh: for the child is the fleſh and ſubſtance of the father and mother, and both their fleſh is vnited in their children. Fourthly, becauſe of the right and power the husband hath ouer the body of his wife, and the wife ouer her husband. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was not</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eua <hi>aſhamed of their nakednes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe that externally, neither heat not cold, nor any thing elſe could hurt their body, internally there was no inordinat affection in the ſoule: but perfectly the inferior part of the ſoule did obey the ſuperior. And thirdly, becauſe there was nothing to be ſeene in their bodies, but that which was comely and decent; and therefore, <hi>Nihil putabant volandum, quia nihil ſenſerant refr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>andum,</hi> Aug. <hi>li.</hi> 11. <hi>de Gen. Cap.</hi> 1.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:12378:40"/>
            <head>Queſtions on the third Chapter.</head>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVHat is meant by the Serpent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not the diuell: for ſo theſe words ſhould be metaphorically vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood: but this is a hiſtory, and no allegory, nor the image of a Serpent, for it was not a picture, but a real Serpent that was curſed, neither was it a naturall Serpent that did ſpeake: for ſpeech and reaſoning doe naturally belong to men, not to beaſts: for they neither haue reaſonable ſoules, nor the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſpeech: but it was the deuill that ſpake in the Serpent, vſing the ſame as his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to deceiue. So then, there was both a ſerpent, which is proued both by the ſpeech of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the puniſhment inflicted on the Serpent; &amp; beſides, the deuill, which is knowne both by his ſpeech and reaſoning with <hi>Eua,</hi> as alſo by the teſtimonie of Chriſt, calling the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill a manſlayer from the beginning, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why was not</hi> Eua <hi>afraid to conferre with the Serpent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the ſerpent <hi>(as all other creatures)</hi> was ſubiect and obedient to man, neither durſt they, nor could they afray him or hurt him, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12378:41"/>
was there any place for feare in that happy eſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why did Satan vſe rather the Serpent, then any other creature?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, becauſe God did not ſuffer him to take any other creature. Secondly, becauſe the Serpent, of al other creatures, is moſt ſubtil, deceitfull, prone to hurt, and deceiue man: the Serpent is prudent to ſaue it ſelfe: therefore it is ſayd, <hi>Be wiſe as Serpents,</hi> Math. 10. and crafty to deceiue others, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>The Serpent by his craftines deceiued</hi> Eua, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>Chap.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Seeing it was the diuell in the ſerpent, that deceiued</hi> Eua, <hi>why doth not</hi> Moſes <hi>ſignifie ſo much?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> writeth a hiſtory, and not a commentary, therefore all that is ſpoken heere, he doth attribute to the Serpent, becauſe <hi>Eua</hi> ſaw the Serpent, and conferred with the Serpent: but Satan ſhe ſaw not.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doe theſe words meane,</hi> Your eyes ſhall be opened?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This is meant of a further degree of knowledge, which <hi>Eua</hi> had not as yet: for the eyes of the body were opened already, and good and euill is not the obiect of bodily eyes, but of the minde, which is the eye of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:12378:41"/>
               <hi>Q. What is that,</hi> You ſhall be as Gods?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By Gods, may bee vnderſtood Angels, which are called Gods in Scripture: but here is rather meant the perſons of the Trinity: as verſ. 22. <hi>Behold,</hi> Adam <hi>is become as one of vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Did not</hi> Eua <hi>ſee that this tree was good till now?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: ſhe ſaw before but ſimply, but now ſhe ſeeth it with an ardent deſire to eate of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why did God ſuffer</hi> Eua <hi>to be tempted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That there might bee an occaſion for the manifeſtation both of Gods iuſtice in puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the wicked, and of his mercy in ſauing the repentant. Secondly, To ſhew vs, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhee had all happineſſe in that eſtate, yet ſhe ſhould not haue beene free of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Thirdly, That we might learne to arme our ſelues againſt Satan: for if he durſt tempt in the eſtate of innocency, &amp; in Paradiſe, what will he not doe to vs now, being driuen out of Paradiſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What was the firſt ſinne of</hi> Eua?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Incredulity, in not beleeuing Gods threatning. Secondly, Pride, deſiring to bee like God. Thirdly, A lye, ſaying, that God did forbid to touch the tree. Fourthly, Gluttony, in deſiring the fruit which was forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Scandall, in drawing <hi>Adam</hi> to the ſame ſin.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12378:42"/>
Sixthly, A fooliſh excuſing of her ſinne to God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was the Diuell ſo earneſt to te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Eua?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe he hated God, and would not haue man to glorifie, but to anger him. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Becauſe of his pride and enuy: for hee could not abide that man ſhould bee in ſuch happineſſe, himſelfe being in miſery.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did</hi> Adam <hi>eate of this fruit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Partly, through the inſtigation of his wife; partly, through curioſity, deſiring to try what kinde of ſinne this ſhould be, which God did prohibit: ſo
<q>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> in vetit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſemper, cupi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſque nega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Was</hi> Adam <hi>deceiued alſo, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> was?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: <hi>Adam</hi> was not ſeduced, but the woman, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. For <hi>Eua</hi> did not deceiue <hi>Adam,</hi> becauſe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e thought all was true that Satan ſpoke: but Satan deceiued <hi>Eua,</hi> becauſe he made her beleeue that, which he knew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was falſe. Secondly, <hi>Eua</hi> confeſſed that ſhe was deceiued, but <hi>Adam</hi> doth not ſay that he was deceiued, but, <hi>The woman gaue to me, and I did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Was the ſinne of</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eua <hi>the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſin that euer was committed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:12378:42"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> If wee doe conſider one ſin with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then wee ſay, that <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne was not the greateſt, for the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt is greater; but if we reſpect the circumſtances of <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne; to wit, the place, Paradiſe, where no occaſion of ſinne was; the time when he ſinned, immediately after his creation, at the firſt encounter yeelding to his enemy; the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the perſon that ſinned, <hi>Adam,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing created to Gods owne Image: if wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard alſo that infinite hurt and miſery that hath faine vpon mankinde, by that ſinne of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi> we muſt confeſſe, that it is the greateſt ſinne that euer man committed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Whether was the ſinne of</hi> Adam <hi>or</hi> Eua <hi>greatest?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> If we conſider both their perſons, then <hi>Adam</hi> did ſinne more grieuouſly, becauſe hee was wiſer and ſtronger than <hi>Eua,</hi> and he was the head of the woman: for this cauſe ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>that by one man ſinne entred into the world,</hi> Rom. 5. yet in two reſpects, <hi>Eua's</hi> ſin was greater than <hi>Adams:</hi> firſt, in that ſhe did beleeue the Serpent more than God; which <hi>Adam</hi> would not haue done: ſecondly, in that ſhe did entice <hi>Adam</hi> to the ſame ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How were their eyes opened after the eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this fruit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:12378:43"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> They were not blinde before, nor had they now more libertie of will than they had, or greater knowledge: but now they know e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill by experience, which before they knew by ſcience; and their eyes are ſayd to be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, becauſe they perceiue, their nakedneſſe is ignominious, and their affections inordinate, which before were decent and holy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why did they couer their members, after the eating of the forbidden fruit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they were aſhamed of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe: ſecondly, by this they thought to hide their ſinne, but in vaine: for none can hide ſinne but God; therefore <hi>bleſſed is he whoſe ſinne is co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered, Pſal.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did they couer their priuy members?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe their inordinate luſt beganne moſt to appeare heere: ſecondly, theſe are the inſtruments of generation, which then became ſinfull; therefore all people are aſhamed to ſee thoſe parts, becauſe ſinne comes by generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Hence circumciſion (the ſigne of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) was on this part of the body, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did they take the leaues of the Figge tree?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the leaues of the Figge tree are broadeſt, or elſe, becauſe their guilty conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences accuſing them; and being in feare, they
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12378:43"/>
tooke of the leaues of this tree which was neereſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is meant heere by the noyſe of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This ſometimes ſignifieth thunder, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odus</hi> 9. ſometimes any ſound, <hi>Ezec.</hi> 12. ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Gods diſtinct voyce like thunder, <hi>Iohn</hi> 12. here it ſignifieth ſome fearefull noyſe and ſound, by which God would ſignifie, that now he was comming to encounter with <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ſignifieth the winde of the day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This is a deſcription of the euening: for at the going downe of the Sunne in thoſe places, that are neere the Mediterranean Sea, commonly the wind doth blow from the Sea; and as God came to iudge <hi>Adam</hi> in the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſo will he come to iudge all mankinde in the euening of the world, with the ſound of the Trumpet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How did God ſpeake to</hi> Adam <hi>heere?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God ſpeaketh in Scripture ſometime internally by his Spirit, ſometimes externally, either by Angels, or by men. Heere then it is like, that Chriſt ſpake in the forme of man; for in this forme he did oftentimes appeare to the Fathers of old; and in the fulneſſe of time, this word was made fleſh, and dwelt with vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why did not God accuſe Satan, as hee did the man and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> woman?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:12378:44"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe Satan was already condemned for his pride, but the other two were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ſentence of condemnation; therefore he would not condemne them, till he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Whether did God courſe the Diuell or the Serpent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He curſed both: the Diuel myſtically, and the Serpent literally; the diuell as the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal agent, and the Serpent as his inſtrument: but this curſe is pronounced of the Serpent onely; becauſe it was the Serpent that <hi>Eua</hi> did ſee and ſpeake to, and the Diuell did lurke within the Serpent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How could the creeping on the belly, and the eating of the dust, be a puniſhment and a curſe, ſeeing this was naturall to the Serpent before mans fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Serpents creeping before was pleaſant, now it is painefull; then it was come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, now it is baſe, execrable and contemptible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why did God curſe the Serpent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To augment Satans griefe the more, who vſed him for his organ in this wicked ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: ſecondly, becauſe the Serpent being Satans inſtrument, was the occaſion of mans fall: as the beaſt with whom any man did lie, was to be ſtoned, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 20. thirdly, becauſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12378:44"/>
by this God wil ſhew, how much he abhorreth ſinne, in puniſhing for mans wickednes dumb and ſenſleſſe creatures; therefore the earth was curſed for <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne, the beaſts and fowles were drowned for the ſinne of the firſt world, the Cities that entice the Iſraelites to Idolatrie, muſt be burnt; yea the cattell and euery thing in thoſe Cities, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. yea the dumbe creatures for mans ſinne, were daily of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vp in ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is meant by the VVomans Seed, and the Serpents ſeed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the Womans ſeed, is meant eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſt, the Womans Seed, according to the fleſh; and with him, all the faithfull: by the Serpents ſeed, are meant both the rauenous beaſts, which naturally hate mankinde, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo wicked men, which are called Serpents in Scripture, and generation of vipers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is meant heere by the Head and the Heele?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the Head of the Serpent, is meant the power of the Diuell, ſinne and death; by which he woundeth vs: by the Heele, is meant the humanity of Chriſt and his members, which Satan did hurt by the death of the Croſſe, and woundeth yet by perſecuting his members.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:12378:45"/>
               <hi>Q. How can the multiplication of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> conceptions be a puniſhment for ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The conceptions of the woman are a puniſhment, becauſe ſomtimes their concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are imperfect and deformed: ſecondly, many children, being conceiued, do periſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come to maturity: thirdly, many children are wicked and rebellious, not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the wombe that bare them with anguiſh, nor the pappes which ſuckled them with dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Theſe are great puniſhments inflicted on women for the ſinne of <hi>Eua:</hi> fourthly, her conceptions are a puniſhment; for many infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities doe accompany a woman that is with childe, as ſwimming: in the head, tooth-aches, perturbations in the minde, vitioſities in the ſtomacke; as to refuſe good and wholeſome meates, to deſire to eate thoſe things which Nature (being ſound) abhorreth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the reaſon that women doe bring forth their children in ſorrow?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Gods decree in puniſhing the ſinne of <hi>Eua:</hi> ſecondly, the narrow paſſage of the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with a dilatation and ſtretching out of the internall parts therof, cauſeth moſt ſharp and ſenſible paines: hence the Scripture compares exquiſit ſorrow and paine, with the ſorrowes of the child-birth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48. <hi>Mica.</hi> 4. <hi>Reu.</hi> 12.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12378:45"/>
but this paine ſhould not haue bene in the ſtate of innocency.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Whereon was the ground curſed for</hi> Adams <hi>ſake?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In that it did not bring forth fruite of it owne accord, as it ſhould haue done, if <hi>Adam</hi> had not ſinned, or at leaſt, with little labour. Secondly, In that it brought forth noxious, &amp; fruitleſſe, and poyſonable herbes after the Fall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why did</hi> Adam <hi>call his wife</hi> Eua, <hi>the mother of liuing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe by this name hee would teſtifie his faith, in beleeuing that Chriſt, the Seed of the woman, ſhould bring that life againe to man which be had loſt by his ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Did God make coates of ſkinnes for</hi> Adam <hi>and his wife?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: but whether God killed ſome beaſt, or whether he created the skinnes of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or of ſome matter, it is vncertaine; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, by thoſe skins he did put <hi>Adam</hi> in mind of his mortality, and that he had neede of clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, both for his body, which now was to be ſubiect to infirmities, as alſo for his ſoule, which now was defiled with ſinne, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt bee clothed with the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt; which garment hee did put on by beleeuing that Chriſt, the Lambe of God,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12378:46"/>
ſhould bee killed to clothe his naked ſoule; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this beaſt was killed to clothe his naked bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: theſe skinnes alſo doe ſignifie our morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: for, as theſe beaſts were killed, ſo wee muſt kill our ſinnes; for this cauſe, the skinnes of the Sacrifices were giuen to the Prieſts, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 7. <hi>Eli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Saints, did weare skinnes. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did God doth them with skinnes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt; to ſhow them that it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> lawfull for them to kill beaſts, although not to eate, yet to clothe their bodyes. Secondly, To teach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſobriety, for thoſe were skinnes; not Silke, Purple, or cloth of Gold, which are not worth ſo much for neceſſity, as for pride. Thirdly, that this firſt <hi>Adam</hi> might in ſame ſort, be a type of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> Ieſus, for this was cloathed with the skinnes of dead beaſts: ſo Chriſt with our dead ſins; for he became ſin for vs, that we might be made the righteouſneſſe of God in him: &amp; ſo our <hi>Iacob</hi> tooke our fleſh and skin, and in it receiued the bleſſing for vs.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was it needefull that</hi> Adam <hi>ſhould be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed now after his Fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes. Firſt, to hide his nakedneſſe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, to defend his body from the iniuries of the aire. Thirdly, To aſſure him, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee was a ſinner, yet God would not
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12378:46"/>
quite forget him, and caſt him away.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did God ſay, that</hi> Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>was like to him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By theſe words God would ſhew how worthy <hi>Adam</hi> was to be ſcorned, who thoght to bee like to any of the three perſons in the Trinity, for eating of the forbidden fruite: ſo this word <hi>(vs)</hi> doth not ſignifie Angels, but the three perſons of the Trinity.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did God driue</hi> Adam <hi>out of the garden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To let him ſee how fooliſhly hee had done, in giuing more credit to his wife then to him. Secondly, to keepe the tree of Life from him, leſt he ſhuld abuſe it, by thinking to haue life by it, ſeeing he had now violated. Gods Law; for although this tree was a ſigne of life before his Fall, now it is none. Thirdly, that by driuing him from this tree of Life, he might ſeek for a better life then this tree could yeeld, euen that heauenly life, which is hid with Chriſt in God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When was</hi> Adam <hi>caſt out of Paradiſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That ſame day he ſinned: for he being now a ſinner, and rebellious againſt God, was not fit to ſtay any longer in that holy place: but what day of the weeke he was caſt out, is vncertaine; yet it is thought the eighth day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his creation, he was caſt out, in the euening of that day: for Satan did not ſuffer him to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12378:47"/>
ſtay long there vntempted: yet I do not hold that he was caſt out that ſame day he was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated: for ſo many things as fell out betweene his creation and caſting out of Paradiſe, could not be done all in ſuch a ſhort ſpace as a piece of a day; for the beaſts were created the ſixth day, before man was. Secondly, in ſuch a ſhort time <hi>Adam</hi> could not haue perceiued the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and happineſſe of that place; therefore he was not caſt out that ſame day hee was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why would God haue</hi> Adam <hi>to till the ground?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe now the ground was curſed, and would not yeeld fruite without hard la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Secondly, by this ſeruill worke, he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would put him in remembrance of his ſinne, which brought him to this miſery: yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God mitigated his hard labour, in free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euery ſeuenth yeere from his tillage, to put them in mind of that eaſe they loſt by ſin, which was reſtored againe ſpiritually by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is meant heere by the</hi> Cherubins <hi>and the fiery</hi> Sword?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not fearefull viſions, nor the torrid Zone, nor a fire compaſſing Paradiſe like a wall, neither the fire of Purgatory, as <hi>Theodore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12378:47"/>
Aquinas, Lyranus,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſius</hi> do i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine: but by the Cherubins we vnderſtand the Angels, which did appeare oftentimes with wings, as <hi>Daniel</hi> 1.9. and the figures of theſe were wrought in the tabernacle, <hi>Exo.</hi> 25. By the fiery ſword, we vnderſtand moſt ſharpe and two-edged ſwords, which the Angels in the forme of men did ſhake, by the which ſhaking and ſwift motion the ſwords did ſeem to <hi>Adam,</hi> to gliſter like fire, for more terror, left he ſhould attempt re-entrance there. The Angels alſo haue appeared at other times, with ſwords in their hands, as we read, <hi>Numbers</hi> 22. of the Angel that met <hi>Balaam;</hi> and of that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel that <hi>Dauid</hi> did obſerue with a ſword in his hand, 1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 21.16.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why are theſe Angels called Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they did appeare with wings: in the Tabernacle and the Temple they were wrought with two wings: they appeared to <hi>Eſay,</hi> with 6. wings, who are called in the 6. of <hi>Eſay,</hi> Seraphins, becauſe they are inflamed with the loue of God: they appeare with wings, to ſignifie there ſwiftneſſe and diligence in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Gods commandements.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:12378:48"/>
            <head>Queſtions on the fourth Chapter.</head>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVHat is the ſubiect of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Concerning the propagation of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, eſpecially of <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> in whoſe perſons were to bee ſeene the wicked and the Church of God. <hi>Caine</hi> ſignifieth poſſeſſion: this is a fit name to the wicked; for they ſeeke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but poſſeſſions and honours in this world, and therefore <hi>Caine</hi> built a City: ſo the wicked laboureth to bee ſecure, to haue reſt and eaſe in this world: but <hi>Abel</hi> ſignifieth va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and ſorrow: ſo is the eſtate of the godly, their life here is but vanity, and they account all things but vanity, their life is ſorrow, they weepe for their ſins, and for the vanities of this world, and becauſe they are perſecuted by the poſterity of <hi>Caine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When was</hi> Caine <hi>borne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> After <hi>Adam</hi> was caſt out of Paradiſe: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or there he remained but a ſhort while, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it fit, that in Paradiſe, a place holy, and the tipe of heauen, any carnall copulation, which now was ſinfull, ſhould be committed.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did</hi> Eua <hi>ſay, I haue obtained a ſonne
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12378:48"/>
of the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe ſhe was glad, thinking ſhe had borne the promiſed Seed, that ſhould tread downe the Serpents head: but ſhe was decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, for he was reiected, although hee was the firſt borne, and therefore a King &amp; Prieſt, and <hi>Abel,</hi> whom ſhee counted vanity, was choſen, and his ſacrifice accepted.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is it ſayd that</hi> Abel <hi>was a feeder of ſheepe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſignifie that <hi>Abel</hi> was the figure of Chriſt: for as he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was killed by his brother <hi>Caine,</hi> ſo was Chriſt of his brethren the Iewes: as <hi>Abels</hi> ſacrifice was receiued, ſo was that perfect Sacrifice of Chriſt accepted of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as a full Propitiation for our ſins; and as <hi>Abel</hi> was a ſhepheard, ſo was Chriſt the true Shepheard, <hi>that laid downe his life for his ſheepe ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherein was</hi> Abels <hi>ſacrifice better then</hi> Cain's?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In that it was of the beſt and fatteſt, ſignifying that the beſt things muſt be giuen to God. Secondly, it proceeded of faith and loue that <hi>Abel</hi> carried to God, <hi>Hebrewes.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How did</hi> Cain <hi>know, that God reſpected the ſacrifice of</hi> Abel?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:12378:49"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> By ſome viſible ſigne, as by fire from heauen conſuming the ſacrifice; for ſo he vſed to ſhew afterward, that he liked the ſacrifice by ſending fire, as <hi>Leuit.</hi> 9. <hi>Iud.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why doth God ſay, that</hi> Abels <hi>deſire ſhould be ſubiect to his brother?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Caine</hi> was the firſt borne, and therefore, by nature, had great priuiledges o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his younger brethren; which words God ſpeakes, to reſtraine him from hurting <hi>Abel:</hi> for though God accepted <hi>Abels</hi> ſacrifice, yet he would not take away the honour of <hi>Caines</hi> Birth-right, and the priuiledges that followed the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhy did</hi> Caine <hi>kill his brother</hi> Abel?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, for enuy, becauſe God accepted his ſacrifice, and therefore he thought, that <hi>Abel</hi> ſhould haue obtained his birth-right: ſecondly, by the inſtigation of Satan, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the holy life of <hi>Abel,</hi> thought, that of him ſhould come the promiſed Seede; ſo hee beganne already to perſecute Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Wherein was</hi> Caines <hi>anſwer to God, euill?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In three things: firſt, in that it was a lie: ſecondly, in that it was impious: for hee lied not to man, but to God: thirdly, in that it was vnreuerent; <hi>Am I my brothers keeper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:12378:49"/>
               <hi>Q. Why is it ſayd, that</hi> Abels <hi>bloud did crie to God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To expreſſe the wickedneſſe of this ſinne. In Scripture foure kindes of ſinne doe crie to God: firſt, murder, as in this place: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that fearefull ſinne of <hi>Sodome, Gen.</hi> 18. thirdly, the oppreſſion of the poore, <hi>Exodus</hi> 3. fourthly, the keeping backe of the labourers hire, <hi>Iames 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat is</hi> Caines <hi>puniſhment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, he was accurſed: that is, depriued of Gods loue and fauor, and hated of all good men, and he was the firſt man that was curſed: as the Serpent his father was the firſt creature that was curſed, becauſe both the Diuell and <hi>Caine</hi> were murtherers; <hi>Adam</hi> was not cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but the earth for him: ſecondly, the earth alſo is curſed for <hi>Caines</hi> ſin, and made vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: thirdly, he is made a vagabond and fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue: ſignifying that he ſhould be ſo troubled with the ſting of his guilty conſcience that he ſhould be in continuall feare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVas</hi> Caines <hi>ſinne greater than he could beare?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for his ſinne was not greater than Gods mercy, &amp; his puniſhment was not grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than Gods iuſtice could inflict: and ſo, by theſe words hee either accuſeth God of iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:12378:50"/>
in ſaying his puniſhment is greater than he can beare; or elſe he deſpaireth, if he ſay, his ſinne is greater than he can beare: and ſo he ſinneth now more fearefully than before: for before, he ſinned againſt his neighbor; here he ſinnes againſt God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat meaneth</hi> Caine, <hi>when hee ſaith, he ſhall be cast out from Gods face?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By Face, either he meanes his preſence in the Church: and in this ſence, to be caſt out from Gods face, is to be excommunicated out of the Church; or by his face, wee may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand his fauour and protection, as often in Scripture: alſo in this ſence, to be caſt out from Gods face, is to loſe his loue, care and fauour; as to haue his face, is to haue all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhy was hee afraid to be killed, ſeeing there were no more men now but</hi> Adam?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Although <hi>Moſes</hi> doth not mention o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men at this time, becauſe his drift is to ſpeake only of the propagation of the Church, yet we muſt know, that now when <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> was killed, mankinde was multiplied; for hee was killed the 129. as ſome, or the 130. yeere of the world, as others doe thinke.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat it meant by the ſeuen-fold puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they ſhall ſuffer who ſhall kill</hi> Caine?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:12378:50"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> By this is either vnderſtood, that they ſhall be puniſhed to the ſeuenth generation, or elſe, by ſeuen-fold is vnderſtood manifold, as often in Scripture. So then, hee that did kill <hi>Caine,</hi> ſhould be moſt ſeuerely puniſhed: not onely for murthering a man, but alſo for mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering ſuch a man as was marked by God, that he ſhould not be murthered.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But why would not God haue</hi> Caine <hi>killed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, to ſhew that he abhors murther: ſecondly, hee would haue him to liue long in beare and torment: thirdly, that by him, liuing ſo long in torment and miſery, others might be warned to abhorre murther: fourthly, that hee might haue the longer time to repent him for his ſinne.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat marke was this that God ſet vpon</hi> Caine?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Whether it was a marke on his body, or madneſſe, and feare in his minde, it is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; yet it was ſome reall and viſible ſigne, that men might be warned by, not to meddle with him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is it vnderstood, that</hi> Caine <hi>went <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from Gods preſence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Heere his preſence doth not ſignifie his knowledge and power; for none can flee from that, as <hi>VVhither ſhall I flee from thy preſence?
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:12378:51"/>
Pſalme</hi> 139. and <hi>Ionas</hi> thought to haue fled from this preſence, <hi>Ionas</hi> 1. But his preſence doth ſignifie heere, the place of his worſhip, where he ſhewed his preſence, and that is his Church; or elſe, he went out of Gods preſence, that is, he was depriued of Gods loue and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did</hi> Caine <hi>build a Citie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> For his better ſecurity, for hee was in continuall feare: ſecondly, becauſe hee was worldly-minded, placing his happineſſe in the cities and forts of this world, and not looking for that city whoſe builder and maker is God: thirdly, that he might the more ſecurely tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize and prey vpon other mens goods and lands: for he is the firſt King and Conquerour in the world: and therefore Kings ſhould not delight in conquering kingdomes with bloud, leſt they be counted the ſucceſſours of <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Nimrod,</hi> that mighty Hunter; for, <hi>Magna imperia ſunt magna latrocinia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhen did</hi> Caine <hi>build this Citie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not when <hi>Henoch</hi> was borne, for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there was no great need to build; ſeeing there were but few perſons in the world; but in his old age; for <hi>Caine</hi> liued a long time, and now man-kinde was greatly multiplied.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhy did he call his Citie</hi> Henoch, <hi>and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:12378:51"/>
not by his owne name</hi> Caine?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe his owne name was odious to the world, in reſpect of his murther, therefore he would not diſgrace his citie, and thoſe that dwelt therein: ſecondly, becauſe he loued <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> exceedingly; therefore he would immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talize his name.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is it vnderstood, that</hi> Iabel <hi>was the father of them that dwelt in tents, and had cattell?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He was the inuenter of ſhepheardry, &amp; of feeding of cattel, now <hi>Abel</hi> being dead: for tents heere ſignifie ſuch tents as ſhepheards doe vſe, and not thoſe that ſouldiers doe vſe in warres.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Who were the firſt Inuenters of Muſicke, and Smiths craft?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not <hi>Pythagoras, Linus, Orpheus,</hi> or <hi>Vulcan,</hi> but <hi>Iubal,</hi> and <hi>Tubal-Caine,</hi> the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of <hi>Caine;</hi> ſo wee ſee, that in externall things, <hi>Caine</hi> and his poſterity were bleſſed, as the wicked are generally in this life, but the inheritance of the Saints is in heauen.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was it lawfull for</hi> Lamech <hi>to haue two wiues?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for it was againſt the firſt inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Marriage: ſecondly, againſt the law of Nature, which doth ſhew, that one ſhould be content with one: thirdly, this pluralitie of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:12378:52"/>
wiues did ariſe of incontinency and luſt, and not of deſire to propagate to the increaſe of the Church, as many Saints haue done.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is meant by theſe words,</hi> I would ſlay a man in my wound, &amp;c?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Heere <hi>Lamech</hi> perceiuing that hee was hated for his cruelty, braggeth to his wiues of his ſtrength, that although he were wounded, yet hee were able to kill a man; this hee did ſpeake, to make his wiues and others feare him the more: the Hebrewes thinke, that <hi>Lamech</hi> did kill <hi>Caine</hi> in the wildernes, thinking him to be a wilde beaſt; and perceiuing that it was <hi>Caine,</hi> he killed alſo the yong man that decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What meaneth theſe words,</hi> If <hi>Caine</hi> ſhall be auenged ſeuen-fold, then <hi>Lamech,</hi> &amp;c?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Either he ſpeaketh this, to affray o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from killing him, although he was a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, &amp; ſo making a deriſion of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hee had laid vpon <hi>Caine,</hi> as if hee woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſay; If he that killeth <hi>Caine,</hi> ſhall be puniſhed ſeuen-fold: then he that killeth me, ſhall be puniſhed ſeuenty ſeuen-fold; that is, a great deale more: or elſe, by theſe words he ſeemeth to repent for his murther: as if hee would ſay, Was <hi>Caine</hi> puniſhed ſo hardly for his murther? then I am woorthy of a ſeuenty ſeuen-fold
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:12378:52"/>
worſe puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was</hi> Sheth <hi>the third ſonne of</hi> Adam? <hi>or had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y more beſides thoſe three mentioned in</hi> Geneſis?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is credible, that in the ſpace of an hundred and thirty yeeres; (for in the hundred and thirtieth yeere <hi>Sheth</hi> was borne) <hi>Adam</hi> had many more children than thoſe three, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> were created perfect, and apt for procreation. So alſo it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that the world ſhould be multiplied, according to GODS Decree, <hi>Increaſe and multiply.</hi> But theſe three <hi>Moſes</hi> onely nameth, becauſe of all the reſt, they were moſt eminent; <hi>Abel,</hi> the ripe of Chriſt and the Church, which are <hi>Abels,</hi> that is, mourners in this life: <hi>Caine,</hi> the tipe of the diuell and his Church, and the father of the wicked; <hi>Sheth,</hi> the origin and roote of the Church, the Father of Chriſt: ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the origin of all mankind after the flood: for <hi>Abel</hi> was killed, and <hi>Caines</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity drowned.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why doth</hi> Eua <hi>ſay, that God hath put an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſeed to me, in ſtead of</hi> Abel, <hi>ſpeaking of</hi> Sheth, <hi>and not of any other of her ſonnes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Sheth</hi> was likeſt <hi>Abel,</hi> of all <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'s</hi> children, both in religion toward God, vprightnes of life towards men, and in loue
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:12378:53"/>
and reuerence towards his Parents.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What did</hi> Enoch <hi>ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Sorrowfull or miſerable: hee alſo was a tipe of the Church, which is preſſed, although not oppreſſed with ſorrow and miſery in this life.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhy doth</hi> Moſes <hi>ſay, that in his dayes men began to call on the name of the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſignifie, that now men began to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, more publikely then they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to exhort the people to repentance, to preach openly: but wee muſt not thinke that God was not worſhipped at all till now: for <hi>Adam</hi> did worſhip God, and taught his ſonnes <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Caine</hi> to ſacrifice, and <hi>Sheth</hi> alſo was an holy man, and tipe of Chriſt and of the Church.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>Questions on the fift Chapter.</head>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVHy doth</hi> Moſes <hi>rehearſe the ten generations of</hi> Adam?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, to ſhew the genealogie of Chriſt the promiſed ſeed. Secondly, becauſe hee is to ſpeake of <hi>Enochs</hi> tranſlation, therefore hee would ſhew his generation. Thirdly, to ſhew that amongſt theſe multitudes, God had his
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:12378:53"/>
Church, although it was then ſmall: for God hath neuer wanted ſome ſince the creation, who doe worſhip him, and call vpon his name.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why doth</hi> Moſes <hi>ſay here, that God did both create and make man? and what is meant by</hi> Adam <hi>here?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He doth diſtinguiſh creation from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: for to be made, is to be formed of ſome pre-exiſtant matter: but to be created, is to bee produced of nothing: then both theſe words he vſed, to ſignifie the diuers poducing of the ſoule and body. The ſoule is created, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is produced of nothing: the body is made, becauſe of ſome thing: and by <hi>Adam,</hi> he meaneth both the man and the woman, giuing them one name, to ſignifie that they are both of one fleſh.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is it vnderſtood, that</hi> Adam <hi>begat a ſonne after his image?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, by his image, we vnderſtand his nature and ſubſtance. Secondly, his reaſon and power he had ouer all other creatures. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the corruption of his nature: ſo that now <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> being ſinfull and mortall, begetteth ſinfull and mortall children: then <hi>Sheth</hi> was begotten after the image of <hi>Adam,</hi> a man indued with reaſon, and dominion ouer the creatures,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:12378:54"/>
ſubiect to ſin and death as <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is it not ſayd, that</hi> Adam <hi>did beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Caine <hi>and</hi> Abel <hi>after his image?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe a part of this image doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in bearing rule ouer the creatures, which dominion <hi>Abel</hi> had not being taken away by vntimely death; and from <hi>Cain</hi> this power was taken away, becauſe he was accurſed, and the earth commanded not to yeeld her increaſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth this name</hi> Sheth <hi>ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To be ſet, or appointed in ſtead of <hi>Abel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and as <hi>Abel</hi> was the tipe of mortality, ſo <hi>Sheth</hi> is the tipe of our reſurrection for <hi>Adam</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be dead, <hi>Abel</hi> being killed, and <hi>Caine</hi> accurſed: but in the birth of <hi>Sheth,</hi> he ſeemes to reuiue ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine: and as he in <hi>Sheth</hi> was reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ſo we all in Chriſt ſhal be made aliue: and in that <hi>Adam</hi> giueth the ſame name to his ſon that <hi>Eua</hi> did, they both teſtifie their faith and hope they haue in the promiſed Seed.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why are the yeeres of</hi> Adam <hi>and the reſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lled dayes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſignifie, that although our life bee neuer ſo long, it ſhall conſume as dayes; for all yeeres are compoſed of dayes: therefore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day we ſhould be mindfull of Mortality, and thinke, that euery day is the laſt: and wee muſt beſeech God, that hee would teach vs to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:12378:54"/>
number our dayes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the cauſe that</hi> Adam, <hi>and the reſt here named before the Floud, liued ſo long?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, becauſe they liued ſoberly, and were contented with ſimple diet, not pampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their bellies, as now with variety of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes. Secondly, the conſtitution of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes were better then ours, ſtronger, and not ſubiect to diſeaſes. Thirdly, they had more experience and skill in the nature of hearbes and fruits, which they did eate, then wee haue. Fourthly, the earth then brought forth excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenter hearbes for the food of man, then it hath done after the Floud. Fifthly, God would haue them liue ſo long, that Man-kinde might the more be multiplyed. Sixthly, that man might the more commodiouſly finde out Arts and Sciences, which they could not doe without long experience. Seuenthly, the moderate te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perature of the aire was then greater. Eight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they did liue ſo long, that <hi>Adam</hi> might teach them the Creation of the World, his happines in Paradiſe, and reiection from thence, &amp;c. that the knowledge of God and religion, might the better bee eſtabliſhed amongſt them, and propagated by them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat kinde of yeeres were thoſe that</hi> Moſes <hi>mentioneth heere?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:12378:55"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not the yeeres of the Moone, which we call moneths: for by this computation wee ſhould confeſſe, that <hi>Kenan</hi> and <hi>Enoch</hi> did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get ſonnes and daughters before they were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeeres olde, and that <hi>Abraham</hi> being 17. yeeres of age, was a very olde man: but <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> meaneth the yeeres of the Sun, which were equall with our yeeres, as wee haue prooued in the Preface, vpon the ſecond book of our Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhy did</hi> Moſes <hi>ſubioyne vnto euery one of their liues, this particle</hi> (and he died?)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, to ſhew the ineuitable puniſhment and conſequent of ſinne vpon all Man-kinde. And from hence we may conclude, that euery one that dieth, is a ſinner, euen children; for death is the wages of ſinne. I except Chriſt, who died, not becauſe he ſinned, but becauſe he came to deſtroy ſinne, and death, and Satan, that hath the power of death. Secondly, to ſhew the vanity of this life, which is ſo ſhort. Thirdly, to put vs in minde of our mortality, that we might prepare our ſelues for our end: all muſt die, euen thoſe are gone that liued ſo long; and although that wee thinke they liued many yeeres, yet we may truely ſay, that they did not liue one whole day, for none of them li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued 1000. yeeres, which to God is as one day.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:12378:55"/>Q. <hi>VVhat is the cauſe of the great difference betweene the Hebrew copyes, and the tranſlation of the Septuagints, in the computation of the yeeres betweene</hi> Adam <hi>and the Floud?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We cannot ſay, that thoſe ſeuenty In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters, which <hi>Ptolemy</hi> did imploy in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the Hebrew Bible into the Greeke tongue, did erre in their computation, ſeeing they vſe no figures, as the Greekes and Latines doe in this computation; but they vſe the names of their numbers. But rather we thinke, that thoſe that copied out the tranſlation of the Septuagints, out of <hi>Ptolemeus Librarie,</hi> did erre, in miſtaking the Greeke figures; for one letter or figure may eaſily be miſtaken for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: or elſe they were ſomewhat negligent, becauſe they thought theſe numbers of yeeres not to bee neceſſary. But wee muſt adhere to the Hebrew veritie, or elſe, if we follow the Septuagints in their computation, wee muſt yeeld, that <hi>Methuſalem</hi> did liue after the Floud 16. yeeres, which is directly againſt the truth of Gods Word, which affirmeth, that eight ſoules did onely eſcape the Floud, that is, <hi>Noah</hi> and his Family.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Did</hi> Henoch <hi>die, or not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He did not die: ſo witneſſeth <hi>Paul, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> 11. and <hi>Moſes</hi> alſo in this place: for hee
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:12378:56"/>
ſubioynes to euery one of their liues that liued before and after <hi>Henoch,</hi> vntill the Floud <hi>(and he died;)</hi> but of <hi>Henoch</hi> hee ſpeaketh no ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did God tranſlate</hi> Henoch, <hi>that he ſhould not ſee death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, that he might aſſure the faithful, of their reſurrection and life eternall: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe the world did degenerate, &amp; came, as it were, to the height of impietie: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he tooke him away, left he had beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with their wickedneſſe, and ſo be made partaker of their plagues: thirdly, becauſe God would ſhew the world, how highly he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemeth thoſe that walke with him, that is, that obey, loue, and feare him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whither was</hi> Henoch <hi>tranſlated?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not to the earthly Paradiſe; for that was deſtroyed with the Floud: but he was tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to that heauenly Paradiſe, whereof Chriſt ſpeaketh to the good Thiefe on the Croſſe, and whither <hi>Elias</hi> was caught: now, although be dyed not, yet his tranſlation was in ſtead of death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What ſignifieth</hi> Noe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. Rest:</hi> which name his father <hi>Lamech</hi> gaue him, becauſe of the comfort hee ſhould haue of him, thinking that he was the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:12378:56"/>
Seed that ſhould tread downe the Serpents head: or rather, becauſe that he perceiued by the Spirit of prophecie, that he ſhould be the type of Chriſt. For as <hi>Noe</hi> reſtored the world after the Floud: ſo did Chriſt, after the floud of his Fathers wrath, reſtore the world to ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all life: ſecondly, as <hi>Noe</hi> did build the Arke, ſo hath Chriſt built the Church: thirdly, as <hi>Noe</hi> offered ſacrifice, whereby God ſmelled a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of Reſt, and ſaid hee would curſe the ground no more: ſo in Chriſts Sacrifice which he offered on the croſſe, is the Father well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and he will not be angry with his Church for euer.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How was</hi> Noe <hi>a comfort to</hi> Lamech, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſorrow and worke of his hands, and touching the earth which the Lord curſed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By Sorrow, and the workes of our hands, may be vnderſtood ſinne, which is our owne worke; as holineſſe is the work of God: by the earth, which was curſed, wee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the barrenneſſe of the ground, and the hard labor of the husbandmen: for the ground was curſed twice; once for <hi>Adams</hi> ſake, and once for <hi>Caines:</hi> but now <hi>Lamech</hi> comforteth himſelfe, that <hi>Noe</hi> ſhalbe acceptable to God, who, for his ſake, appoynted times and ſeaſons for ſowing and reaping, and gaue <hi>Noe</hi> the skill
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:12378:57"/>
to finde out wine that comforts the heart of man: and alſo, in his time, God did ſweepe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſins of this age, which did grieue <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mech,</hi> with an vniuerſall floud.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which of</hi> Noes <hi>three ſonnes were eldeſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. Iapheth</hi> is the eldeſt, as it is plaine, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.21. <hi>Cham</hi> the youngeſt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.24. but <hi>Shem</hi> is firſt named: Firſt, becauſe in dignity he is preferred before his brethren, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.26. ſo <hi>Abraham</hi> is named before his elder brother, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.26. <hi>Iacob</hi> before <hi>Eſau, Gen.</hi> 28.5. <hi>Eph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raim</hi> before <hi>Manaſſes, Gen.</hi> 48.20. Secondly, <hi>Shem</hi> is firſt named, becauſe of him, <hi>Abram</hi> and his poſterity, the Iſraelites, deſcended, of which <hi>Moſes</hi> is purpoſed to ſpeake moſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did the Patriarches here named, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine ſo long from begetting children, as</hi> Noe, <hi>till he was</hi> 500. <hi>yeeres old, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As they liued longer then wee, ſo they were not ready ſo ſoone to beget children, as we are: for now, when a man is 30. he is in the prime of his yeeres: but then none was ſayd to come to mans eſtate, till hee had bin a 100. yeeres and more. Secondly, <hi>Moſes</hi> drift her is not to ſet downe the names of all the ſons of theſe Fathers, but of ſuch as <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the Iſraelites came; and therefore he omits thoſe firſt borne of whom <hi>Abraham</hi> came not, and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:12378:57"/>
ſpeakes of the youngeſt; as <hi>Mathew,</hi> in deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing Chriſts genealogie, ſpeaketh of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> not of <hi>Iſmael;</hi> of <hi>Iacob,</hi> not of <hi>Eſau;</hi> of <hi>Iudas</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> not of their elder brethren, becauſe of them came not the Lord.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>Questions on the ſixt Chapter.</head>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVHat is vnderſtood by men, that began to multiply?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By men, wee vnderſtand the ſonnes of <hi>Caine,</hi> who, becauſe they tooke many wiues, did increaſe faſter then <hi>Sheths</hi> poſterity; and as they multiplied, ſo did their ſinnes multiply: for the multiplication of mankinde is a bleſſing: but we ſee, the more bleſſings God beſtoweth on vs, the worſe we are.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is meant here by the ſonnes of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not Angels, neither good nor bad, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with bodies, nor without bodies: for they being Spirits, are not moued with carnall luſt; neither was it to drowne them, that God ſent the flood, but to deſtroy man: therefore by the ſonnes of God, is vnderſtood men; for of them only doth God ſpeake here, throughout all the Chapter.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ſort of men were theſe, that are called the ſonnes of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:12378:58"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> Some thinke, they were very tall and mighty men: therefore they are called the ſons of God; as the mountaines of God, the Cedars of God, that is, high and tall hills and Cedars: others thinke, they were the ſonnes of Princes and Iudges, which are called gods in Scripture: others againe ſay, that they are thoſe whereof <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. They that are led by the Spirit of God, they are the ſonnes of God; that they were holy and iuſt men: but they are of ſoundeſt iudgement, that by them vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the poſterity of <hi>Sheth,</hi> who although they degenerated, yet <hi>Moſes</hi> giueth them that honourable title, to ſhew their ingratitude, in forſaking their heauenly Father.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is the poſterity of Sheth called the ſonnes of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe God had ſeparated them from the reſt of the world, as a peculiar people to himſelfe, they did ſerue him and reuerence him as their heauenly Father: ſecondly, becauſe <hi>Sheth</hi> their father was an holy, and iuſt man, &amp; by conſequent, the ſonne of God, both by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption and imitation: therefore God doth honour his poſteritie, in calling them the ſonnes of God, for their father <hi>Sheths</hi> ſake: ſo wee ſee what an honour it is to haue holy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:12378:58"/>
               <hi>Q. Was it vnlawfull for the ſonnes of God to take to themſelues wiues of the daughters of men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: for thoſe daughters of men were <hi>Caines</hi> poſteritie, excommunicated from the Church: for they were the ſons of old <hi>Adam,</hi> becauſe they were not borne agayne by the immortall ſeed of the Word. Now it was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for <hi>Sheths</hi> poſteritie to marry <hi>Caines</hi> daughters, being of a contrary Religion; this kind of matrimony was forbidden afterwards, <hi>Exodus</hi> 34. and <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> 7. For this cauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> would not haue their ſons marry with Canaanites: ſecondly, they tooke thoſe wiues, not for multiplication of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, but to ſatisfie their immoderate luſt: therefore this copulation was vnlawfull, for they ſhould not haue defiled their bodies; as <hi>knowing they are the Temples of the holy Ghost.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How doe we know that theſe were not An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, which are called here the ſonnes of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe Angels are Spirits; not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of any phyſicall matter, nor incloſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bodies, as the ſoules of men; therefore they cannot be moued with carnall luſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Some do thinke they haue bodies, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are heere vnderstood to haue taken them wiues of the daughters of men; how then is it, that they haue no bodies?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:12378:59"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> If they had bodies, they ſhould be ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther celeſtiall or elementall; celeſtiall they are not; for heauenly bodies haue but one kinde of motion, which is to turne round; but Angels aſcend and deſcend, and haue all other kindes of mouing. Elementary they are not; for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is compoſed of Elements, is corruptible; but the Angels are not. If they ſay that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: haue in them but one element; then I would know which it is. Againe, they ſhould graunt, that the bodies of Angels are more ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble than the bodies of men; becauſe in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunarie bodies, the more elements they are compoſed of, the nobler and perfecter they are: and if their bodies are baſer, then their mindes are imperfecter: for there is a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betweene the forme and the matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Cannot Angels beget children?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for they haue no feede fit for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, becauſe they feed not: for ſeede is a part of our food. Againe, if they could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create children, they ſhould be diſtinguiſhed in male and female; for both theſe muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre in procreation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is meant by theſe words,</hi> My Spirit ſhall not alwayes ſtriue with man?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the word Spirit, is not vnderſtood Gods prouidence, nor God himſelfe taken eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:12378:59"/>
nor his wrath and indignation; nor mans ſoule: but Spirit is taken for God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe perſonally, or for the holy Ghoſt, the third perſon in the Trinity; by which Spirit, Chriſt preached in <hi>Noe,</hi> to the diſobedient ſpirits of the old world, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. The meaning then is, My holy Spirit ſhall not contend alwayes (or a long time) with ſinnefull man, by exhorting, conuincing outwardly, and inwardly by the checkes of conſcience, becauſe he is but fleſh; that is, fleſhly-minded, walketh after the fleſh, and not after the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What then is meant by fleſh heere?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not fleſh properly ſo called: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor as it is taken for the nature of man, as <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.14. Chriſt the Word, is ſaid to be made fleſh; but heere it is taken for the corruption of mans nature. Here then God calleth man, whom he had made to his owne Image, fleſh, to make him aſhamed that he hath ſo miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly falne from his firſt integrity: <hi>for</hi> Adam <hi>was made a liuing ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why ſaith God, that the daies of man ſhould be an hundred and twenty yeeres, ſeeing that after the Floud, many did liue till they were aboue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is true, that <hi>Sem</hi> liued fiue hundred yeeres after the Floud, ſome foure hundred, ſome two hundred, and many till <hi>Moſes</hi> time,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:12378:60"/>
liued an hundred and thirty yeeres. So that theſe words muſt not be vnderſtood, as though God, after the Floud, did prolong mans life, onely to an hundred and twenty yeeres: but theſe one hundred and twenty yeers, are meant of that time that God gaue to the firſt world to repent in; ſo long <hi>Noe</hi> preached, and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Arke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. It ſeemes there was an hundred yeers from the vttering of this ſpeech, till the Floud: for</hi> Sem, <hi>after the Floud immediatly, was an hundred yeeres old; and hee was borne when this ſpeech was vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> From the vttering of this ſpeech, vntill the Floud, there was an hundred and twenty yeeres; but this was ſpoken when <hi>Noe</hi> was foure hundred and foureſcore yeeres old, that is, twenty yeeres before he was fiue hundred; and before <hi>Sem</hi> was borne: yet <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of <hi>Sems</hi> generation, before the vttering of theſe words, becauſe ſpeaking of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of the Fathers, from <hi>Adam,</hi> vntill the Floud, he would not leaue out the generation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sem;</hi> although he was borne twenty yeeres after the vttering of theſe words of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What were theſe Giants that are here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They were men of great ſtature of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:12378:60"/>
and therefore ſtrong and powerfull, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo cruell, wicked, ambitious; in Greeke they are called <hi>Gigantes;</hi> that is, engendred of the earth, not as though they were the ſonnes of the earth; as the Poets thought; but becauſe of a great deale of earthly ſubſtance they carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about in their bodies; as alſo, in reſpect of their minds, being earthly-minded: in Hebrue they are called <hi>Nephilim,</hi> from falling, becauſe as Apoſtates they fell from God: and being cruell, they fell on men, and cauſed many, by feare, to fall before them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Then is it true, that there haue beene ſuch mighty men of great ſtature, which wee doe call Giants?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: both ſacred and prophane hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries doe teſtifie ſo much. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith, <hi>libr.</hi> 15. <hi>de Ciuitate Dei,</hi> That he ſawe a tooth of a man, as great as an hundred of ours. <hi>Plinie</hi> recordeth in his ſeuenth book, That in <hi>Creta,</hi> out of a hill, was digged the body of a man of ſixe and forty cubites. The Spies that were ſent to <hi>Canaan,</hi> reported that they ſeemed Graſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers, in compariſon of the Giants of that Land, <hi>Num.</hi> 13. The yron bed of <hi>Og,</hi> king of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> was nine cubites long, and foure cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits broad, <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> 3. <hi>Goliah</hi> of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtins, was a mightie great Giant: and many
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:12378:61"/>
more examples might heere be alledged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. But were theſe Giants begotten of diuels and women, as ſome haue thought?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Seeing theſe Giants were of the ſame ſubſtance and nature that other men are, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring onely in the quantity of their bodies from others, which is no eſſentiall, but accidentall difference, they were men, and begotten of men and women: ſecondly, if diuels had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten them of women, they had beene ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men nor diuels, but a third kinde diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from both; for when two of diuers kinds couple together, they bring forth a third kind different from both: as the Horſe and the Aſſe beget a Mule, which is neither horſe nor Aſſe: now, diuels and women being much more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in nature, could not bring forth Giants, ſeeing theſe were men: thirdly, diuels being ſpirits, cannot procreate, as is already proued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What was the ſinne of the first world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. Moſes</hi> in the fift verſe of this. Chapter deſcribes their wickedneſſe, that it was great: ſecondly, it was vniuerſall, and not amongſt a few: thirdly, it was voluntary, of purpoſe; their whole ſtudy was bent to wickednes: fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it was not for a while, but all the dayes of their life. So then, it was not without cauſe that God ſent a floud of water, to cleanſe the earth
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:12378:61"/>
from that floud of ſinne, with which it was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerflowed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How is it vnderstood, that God was ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, and repented?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God properly repenteth not, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. for it is contrary to his preſcience: neither is he mooued with ſorrow, becauſe he is vnchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.17. But theſe, and ſuch like ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, are attributed to him, after the manner of men: for man, when he repentes, changeth his deed: ſo God is ſayd to repent, when he chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that which he did before; and as man, when he deſtroyeth that which hee loueth, is gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: ſo God is ſayd to bee mooued with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, becauſe he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to deſtroy man, whom he ſo highly loued, and aduanced ouer all the creatures.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why did God ſay he would deſtroy the beasts and the fowles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not becauſe they ſinned: but becauſe they being created for mans vſe, man their Lord and maſter being puniſhed, they muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſuffer with him: for by this, God will ſhew how hee abhorreth ſinne, in puniſhing dumbe beaſts for mans ſin: ſo the beaſt that lyeth with man, muſt bee killed, though it haue no wit, <hi>Leu.</hi> 20.2. When man was drowned, there was no vſe for the beaſts. Thirdly, to augment mans
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:12378:62"/>
puniſhment, and make it the more fearefull, when not only he, but all his goods and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are ſeyzed vpon by Gods wrath.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What meane theſe words, Noah</hi> found grace in the eyes of the Lord?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That is, God was fauorable and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto him. So this phraſe is vſed of <hi>Lot, Gen.</hi> 19. of <hi>Moſes, Exo.</hi> 33. of <hi>Dauid, Acts</hi> 7. of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Luke</hi> 1. Here we ſee, Gods children ſhall not want their commendations, howſoeuer the world deſpiſeth them. <hi>Noe</hi> is here hated of the world: but hee found grace in Gods eyes. Secondly, we ſee, that God will not deſtroy all mankind, but will ſaue a few for propagation of his Church. Thirdly, there was no time ſo corrupt, in which God had not ſome to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherein did</hi> Noe <hi>find grace in Gods eyes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In that hee was preſerued from the flood, when the world was deſtroyed. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in that mankind was preſerued and reſtored by him. Thirdly, in that his dominion ouer the creatures was reſtored, as it was to <hi>Adam.</hi> Fourthly, in that he receiued a larger Patent then <hi>Adam</hi> had, to eate fleſh. Fiftly, in that God did ſmell a ſauor of reſt in his Sacrifice. Sixtly, in that God maketh a couenant wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him, confirmed by the Raine-bow, that hee will
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:12378:62"/>
neuer deſtroy the world againe with water. Seuenthly, in that he was a tipe of Chriſt and his Church; and many other prerogatiues had <hi>Noe,</hi> which were as many pledges of Gods fauour to him. In Hebrew, <hi>Noe</hi> ſignifieth grace, the order of the letters being changed.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is meant here by the generations of</hi> Noe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> His off-ſpring and things that befel him, of which he doth not ſpeake immediatly, but of his vertues, that he was a iuſt &amp; perfect man, &amp;c. And at theſe words the Hebrewes do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin a new ſection which reacheth to the 12. <hi>Chapter:</hi> ſo that they deuide the whole Law into 54. Sections or Lectures, which they read in 52. Sabbaths, and <hi>Geneſis</hi> is deuided into 12. Chapters, or Lectures.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is</hi> Noe <hi>called a iuſt and perfect man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not abſolutely ſo, but in reſpect of that froward generation. Secondly, becauſe he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuored to be ſo, and made a conſcience of his wayes: for God accepts the will, for the deed; and a part, for all. Thirdly, becauſe of his faith: for wee are iuſtified by faith; and the iuſt liueth by faith. Now. <hi>Noe</hi> was made heyre of righteouſnes, which is by faith, as it is in the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 11. And this doth the more commend <hi>Noes</hi> righteouſnes, that in
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:12378:63"/>
ſuch a froward age, he was iuſt and perfect.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is it vnderſtood, that the earth was corrupt before God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the earth, wee vnderſtand men, both becauſe they are the inhabitants of the earth, as alſo becauſe they were earthly-minded. And here, to their diſgrace, they are called earth, as before, fleſh, who ſhould haue bin ſpiritually and heauenly-minded (before God) that is, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly in his ſight: or <hi>Elohius</hi> may ſignifie Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Iudges, here: ſo that in the open ſight of their Iudges, they wrought wickednes. Hence then we ſee, that it was not the Starres, or any naturall cauſes, that raiſed the flood: but only God, being prouoked by ſin.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is it ſaid now, that God looked on the earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not, as though he did not looke before: (for all things are naked before his eyes:) but now hee is ſaid to looke on the earth, becauſe hee commeth to puniſh the earth. And this ſheweth vs, that God did not raſhly, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſedly puniſh the earth, but he looked vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it firſt, that is, he did ſeriouſly conſider, there was great cauſe to puniſh Man-kinde.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is meant here by all Fleſh?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Man-kinde, <hi>Synecdochicè,</hi> and not the beaſts alſo, as the Iewes thought; for they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:12378:63"/>
properly be ſaid to corrupt their way, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they want reaſon. Lawes are not made for them, they are not capable of life eternall, they are not ſubiect to ſinne, and not lyable to puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is meant by way?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Their religion and faith, as <hi>Acts</hi> 18. Secondly, their manners and courſe of life; as malice is called the way of <hi>Cain, Iude,</hi> verſe 11. couetouſneſſe the way of <hi>Balaam,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is it vnderstood, that God destroyed the earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The earth was deſtroyed for the ſinne of man: as in other particular iudgements, mens goods periſhed with them, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.32. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 7.15. yet the earth was not deſtroyed, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of her ſubſtance, but of her ornaments and fertility, which was much diminiſhed by the ſalt water.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why would not God ſaue</hi> Noe <hi>by ſome other meanes, but by the Arke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe, by this meanes God would haue the world to ſee, that his iudgements were comming, when they beheld the Arke preparing; and if they would not repent, they might, at leaſt, be made inexcuſable, who both ſeeing the Arke in making, and hearing <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:12378:64"/>
preaching, did not repent. Secondly, becauſe by this meanes, he would exerciſe <hi>Noe's</hi> faith the more, which was very great; that although the reſt of the world did ſcorne him, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed their owne courſes: yet hee beleeued that God would performe his promiſe. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, although God at all times may worke mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, yet moſt times hee worketh by naturall cauſes: therefore in the Deſart he fed his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with Manna, when he might haue fed them with nothing; ſo hee might haue giuen them <hi>Canaan</hi> without their own helpe; yet he would haue them fight for it: and heere hee might haue preſerued <hi>Noe</hi> more miraculouſly; but this way he thought fitteſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was this Arke like our ſhips?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: but this was like a cheſt or cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin, made not to ſayle, but to ſwimme; and this forme was moſt commodious and capable of ſo many kindes of creatures: and this Arke was admirable, both in reſpect of the long time it was in building, in reſpect of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof, of the end, it was made to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue all kinde of creatures, of the wonderfull preſeruation thereof in that dangerous Flood; as alſo, of many things whereof it was the tipe Concerning this Arke, the Poets haue ſtolne much out of this place.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:12378:64"/>Q. <hi>What kinde of tree was the Arke made of?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The word <hi>Gopher</hi> doth ſignifie the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar, Firre, and Pine trees; ſo it is vncertaine which of thoſe it was made of, neither is it much materiall: but this word is not found in any other place of Scripture.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How large was the Arke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The length was 300. cubits, the bredth 50. and the height was 30. cubits: now a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit is the meaſure from the elbow, to the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers end, containing a foote and a halfe: but if the men of that time were bigger then now, (as it is like) then the cubit was alſo bigger. Then wee muſt not thinke with <hi>Origen,</hi> that thoſe were Geometricall cubits, wherof euery one containes 6. common cubits: for <hi>Moſes</hi> doth not ſpeake here of any other cubits, then hee doth elſe-where: and of no other kinde of cubit doe we reade in Scripture, then of thoſe common cubits aboue-named, as <hi>Exodus</hi> 27. <hi>Deut.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 17. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So then, the Arke, by this reckoning, was ſixe times as long as it was broade, and ten times ſo long as it was high. But how ſo many creatures could be contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in ſo little roome, was not impoſſible for him, that miraculouſly ſent the Flood, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered <hi>Noe</hi> from the ſame: yet if wee duely
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:12378:65"/>
conſider the bigneſſe of the Arke, we ſhal finde there was roome ſufficient for them all.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How could</hi> Noe <hi>and his three ſons build ſo great an Arke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Although they were the chiefe buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, yet we muſt think, there were many more vnder them hired, who laboured in building for their wages, although they beleeued not, and ſo they periſhed with the reſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was there a window in the Arke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: but the Hebrew word is <hi>Zohar,</hi> which ſignifies light: therefore the Hebrewes thought that this was no window, but ſome precious ſtone that was hanged in the Arke, to giue light to the creatures therein: yet we muſt not deny, but that there was a window; for <hi>Noe,</hi> in the eight chapter, is ſayd to open the window, and let out the Rauen and Doue: others ſay, that this <hi>Zohar</hi> was a Lamp or can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, appointed to burne ſo long as <hi>Noe</hi> was in the Arke, becauſe the Sunne did not ſhine all that time: but this is fabulous.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is this</hi> (And in a cubit thou ſhalt finiſh it aboue?)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That is, Thou ſhalt bow the roofe of the Arke but a cubit, ſo that it may bee almoſt flat; but yet ſo, that the water may eaſily ſlide off.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:12378:65"/>Q. <hi>How many roomes or ſtories were there in the Arke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Three roomes: the higheſt for Man and the Fowles; the next, for al kindes of meat and prouiſion for the creatures; the loweſt and third roome for the Beaſts. Theſe three are onely mentioned here: therefore <hi>Origen</hi> was deceiued, that thought there were fiue roomes. As in this Arke there were three roomes, ſo in <hi>Moſes</hi> Tabernacle, and <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple, were alſo three. The Church alſo (fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured by the Arke) hath three ſtates: before the Law; vnder the Law; and vnder Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why would God establiſh his Couenant with</hi> Noe, <hi>before the Arke was built?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To confirme <hi>Noes</hi> faith the more: for he had need of ſuch a promiſe, that went about ſuch a hard and dangerous worke, as the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Arke was. And here wee ſee, that God neuer imployeth his ſeruants in any hard worke, but hee giueth them comfort, ſtrength, and courage to performe it. And ſo it is our part, to rely on Gods promiſes with <hi>Noe,</hi> and not to encline either to the right or left hand.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What couenant was this that God made with</hi> Noe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That he would preſerue him and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:12378:66"/>
in the Floud: and this is a type of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which God hath made with vs in Chriſt. Now this couenant belongeth to <hi>Noe</hi> and his Family: ſo all Gods couenants to the faithfull, and their children alſo. As for <hi>Noe's</hi> ſake, his family was ſaued: ſo for the company of one holy man, many ſhal eſcape in the day of Gods wrath. For <hi>Pauls</hi> ſake, all that were in the ſhip were ſaued. Here, this is called Gods couenant, becauſe he bindes himſelfe to ſaue vs: ſo elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where it is called our couenant, <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.11. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe on our part, we are bound to beleeue and obey him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ſortes of creatures was</hi> Moſes <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to receiue within the Arke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All thoſe that could not liue in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; as men, beaſts and fowles. fiſhes then and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, thoſe creatures that can liue both on the land and in the water, were not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued: ſecondly, the perfect creatures, that is, ſuch as are procreated by commixture of male &amp; female (for the male &amp; female are here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.) Then mice &amp; ſuch like as are inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred of corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, were not receiued. And here <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> is commaunded to receiue two of euery ſort, which in the next chapter is better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained; for of the vncleane, two are receiued, of the cleane, ſeuen; three males and females
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:12378:66"/>
for generation; and one male for the Sacrifice. Heere we ſee, that God for <hi>Noes</hi> ſake, ſaueth all thoſe ſorts of creatures, extending his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, euen to the beaſts, for his ſeruants ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How did</hi> Noe <hi>gather together all theſe cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures? did he hunt for them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: but they came of their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, the Lord leading them thither; and here they are brought to <hi>Noe,</hi> as before to <hi>Adam:</hi> yet, although God brought them to the Arke, notwithſtanding, <hi>Noe</hi> muſt bring them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and place them in the Arke: <hi>Noe</hi> is the type of Chriſts Miniſters, who doe not leade Chriſts ſheepe to the Church, becauſe being moued by Gods Spirit, they come of their owne accords; yet the Miniſter gathereth them together, and doth vnite them by the Word and Sacraments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. If all kindes of meate were layd vp in the Arke for the creatures; then whether, or not, was there alſo fleſh for thoſe creatures, that liued only on fleſh?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, before the Floud, neither man nor beaſt did eate fleſh; but this power of eating fleſh was giuen after the Floud: ſecondly, we doe not reade of any beaſts that were brought into the Arke, for meate, but onely for gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and ſacrifice: thirdly, if there had been
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:12378:67"/>
beaſts in the Arke, for eating, and ſo many as might ſerue for a whole yeere, ſurely there could not be roome enough for them; beſides, their fleſh would haue putrified; and that had beene filthy and lothſome to man: therefore they did not eate fleſh at that time, but either graſſe, fruits, or ſeedes: for theſe they fed vpon when fleſh was wanting. Beſides, God, that cauſed them to come to the Arke, of their own accord, and to remayne ſo long obedient to <hi>Noe,</hi> could alſo ſuſtaine them ſo long without fleſh, onely vpon hearbs: for thoſe were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, at that time, than now: and the tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of thoſe beaſts was ſounder.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why was God ſo carefull to prouide foode for thoſe dumbe creatures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To let vs know and admire his infinite goodneſſe, in not onely creating them for mans vſe, but alſo, in preſeruing them to the ſame end: ſecondly, that by this carefulneſſe of his, we may be induced to loue him the more: thirdly, to depend on him in our extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: for if he had a care of them, when they could not care for themſelues: much more will hee be carefull of vs in our neceſſities: fourthly, he would not ſaue them in the Arke, as he did the Iſraelites in the red Sea: and as <hi>Ionas</hi> in the Whales belly, miraculouſly: but
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:12378:67"/>
he would haue heere both man and beaſt, to vſe the meanes of the Arke, and of the foode he gaue them, for the preſeruation of their life: to teach vs, that we ſhould not deſpiſe the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary meanes that God hath appoynted for the conſeruation of our life: fiftly, to teach all Chriſtians that haue children, wife, or family, to prouide for them things that may ſuſtaine their naturall life: ſeeing God had ſuch care to maintaine the life of theſe creatures, which are not ſo deare to God as men are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the commendation that</hi> Noe <hi>hath heere in the end?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That he did according to all that God commaunded him; therefore he became heire of the Righteouſnes that is by faith, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. Then heere was his glory, not in that he knew Gods commaundements, but in that he did them: ſecondly, he did not a part, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all that was commaunded him: thirdly, his faith and obedience was won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull: if wee ſhould conſider the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances thereof; as the bigneſſe of the Arke, the long and tedious ſpace of an hundreth yeeres, cutting and bringing together ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny trees, the taunts and ſcornes hee did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure of men, the feare he was in, for preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they ſhould all be drowned, the care and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:12378:68"/>
ſollici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ede he had, to gather together ſo much prouiſion for man, beaſts and fowles: yea to bring into the Arke ſo many ſorts of wilde beaſts; and laſtly, to incloſe himſelfe therein for a yeere, as in a Sepulchre: all theſe being conſiderd, ſhall make vs acknowledge, that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Faith and Obedience was worthy of eternall commendations.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whereof was</hi> Noe <hi>and the Arke a tipe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> figure?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Of Chriſt and of the Church: for <hi>Noe</hi> was the tipe of Chriſt, in that <hi>Noe</hi> is reſt: ſo Chriſt is our reſt, &amp; in him we haue reſt for o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſoules; our conſciences haue reſt from the gilt and puniſhment of ſinne, from the condemning and commaunding power thereof; and after this life, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reſt from our labours, euen in the <hi>boſome of</hi> Abraham. Secondly, as <hi>Noe</hi> preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſoone from the flood, ſo hath Chriſt from the floods of Gods wrath. Thirdly, as <hi>Noe</hi> in the Arke of wood did ſaue them, ſo Chriſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſſe of wood, hath ſaued vs. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as out of the Arke there is no ſafety, ſo ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Church there is no ſaluation. Fiftly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Arke was made of diuers ſortes of trees, ſo is the Church of diuers ſorts of men. Sixtly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Ark was a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time in building, ſo hath the Church a long time in making. Seu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hly, as in
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:12378:68"/>
the floud God drowned ſinners, ſo in baptiſme (whereof the flood was a tipe) God drowneth our ſinnes. Eightly, as the plankes of the Arke were ioyned together with Pitch; ſo ſhould the members of the Church be ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with loue. Ninthly, as <hi>Noe</hi> not only built the Arke, but entred therein, ſo Chriſt not only built the Church, but dwels therein. Tenthly, as in the Arke were all ſorts of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſo in the Church are all ſorts of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Eleue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thly, as in the Arke were more beaſts then men, ſo in the Church are more bad then good. Twelftly, as in the Arke was all kind of corporall food for the creatures, ſo in the Church is all kind of ſpirituall food for Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. 13. As in the Arke was a window to giue light to the eies, ſo in the Church is the Word to giue light to the minds. 14. As there was a doore for the creatures to enter into the Arke, ſo Chriſt is the doore, by whom wee enter into the Church. 15. As in the Arke were diuers roomes or ſtories, ſo in the Church are diuers degrees &amp; orders. 16. As the Arke was great and large for all ſorts of beaſts; ſo is the Church for all ſorts of men. 17. As there was but one Arke, one doore, one window; ſo there is but one Church, one Chriſt, one Scripture. 18. As the Rauen went out and came not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:12378:69"/>
but the Doue could finde no reſt, till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> returned to the Arke; ſo the wicked care <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for the Church: but the godly, who repreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the nature and qualities of the Doue, can h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> no reſt for their ſoules but in the Church. 19<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Arke was toſſed vp and downe in the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter with the wind, yet was vpheld by Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo the Church is toſſed vp and downe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſea of this world, with the winds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Satan, of ſinne, of wicked men and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fleſh: yet the Lord vpholds her. 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Arke at laſt reſted on the mountaine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nia;</hi> ſo ſhall the Church on Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Sion, in the Kingdome of glory, when th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> waters ſhall ſettle, and the winds ſhall ceaſe; then thoſe that ſeemed to be dead in the Arke, ſhall come out of the graues; and with ioy ſhall inioy that happy Immortality.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
